<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvarning to the dragon and all his angels</title>
            <author>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A22590</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851058</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851058</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A22590)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 869:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvarning to the dragon and all his angels</title>
                  <author>Eleanor, Lady, d. 1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[110] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by B. Alsop],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXV. [1625]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Lady Eleanor.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ a²  B-N⁴ O²  (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Daniel --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16312:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16312:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VVARNING TO THE DRAGON AND ALL HIS ANGELS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marke yee this wicked perſons, &amp; yee friends of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous MAMMON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>LVKE, XXI.</hi>
               </bibl> Take heed to your ſelues, leſt at any time your hearts be over-charged with Surfetting and Drunkenneſſe, and the Cares of this life, and ſo that day come vpon you vnawares. For as a <hi>SNARE</hi> ſhall it come on all them, that dwell on the face of the whole Earth.</q>
            <p>A SNARE O DEUIL.</p>
            <p>Printed. M.DC.XXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16312:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16312:2"/>
            <head>A GENERALL EPISTLE, TO The fold and Flocke of CHRIST, and to them that are gone aſtray, that ſay they are Apoſtles and Catholiques and are not, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race be to you and Peace from God the Father, and from our Lord <hi>IESUS CHRIST,</hi> who gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for our Sinnes; and in the abſence of his Body for a remmbrance the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Supper, till his ſecond appearing. As often as we taſte thereof, he takes it as a token we are not vnmindfull of his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy that taſted Death it ſelfe for vs; ſo many melting trials and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the innocent Lambe for a brood of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ipers, whoſe damme is Death
<pb facs="tcp:16312:3"/>whoſe ſting is Sinne, he that waſhed vs in his owne Blood vnto whome there is no acceſſe but by Faith; Behold hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and euery eye ſhall ſee him. To him be glory and dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <p>Jt ſeemed good vnto me, having a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vnderſtanding giuen mee in theſe things, and the diſpenſation of them, an office not a trade; to roote out, to pull downe, to build, and to plant, by the grace and bounty of <hi>IESUS</hi> our Lord God. To preſent this Viſitation to your view, joyning you together of the first Arke, and vniuerſall great Houſe, veſſels of Honor and diſhonor, ſome cleane and purified, others having need of purging.</p>
            <p>Former things are come to paſſe, and new things I declare vnto you; no age ſo weake, nor ſex excuſing; when the
<pb facs="tcp:16312:3"/>Lord ſhall ſend and will put his words in their Mouth. He powreth out his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit vpon his hand-maidens; the rich are ſent emptie away, even ſo Father for it ſeemed good in thy ſight.</p>
            <p>Preſſed and conſtrained with obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, and Duty towards you; ſaying no other things then the Prophets and Apostles did ſay ſhould come to paſſe, that yee might know the certainty of thoſe things, wherein yee haue beene inſtructed, whether you will heare or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will forbeare.</p>
            <p>Jt is a ſalue to annoint and open the eyes of the blinde, to bring them that ſit in darkeneſſe a light, to leade them out of the Priſon-houſe; others by meanes of remembrance, (whoſe annoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting long ſince teacheth them all thinges) to ſtirre them vppe;
<pb facs="tcp:16312:4"/>It is a true looking-glaſſe, a large houre-glaſſe, Phiſicke for the ſicke, wholſome for the whole, milke for the young, and meate for the ſtrong. It is vpon Record due, an olde debt One and Twenty hun-yeares ſince; Vnto me is giuen this ſtone to poliſh, vnto me this grace is giuen.</p>
            <p>Jt is as it were a new Song to be ſung before the euerlaſting Throne, a ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Strangers and the Brethren; if we loue them that loue vs, if we ſalute the Brethren only, what doe wee more then others; yea but they come at the laſt houre, others hauing borne the heate and burthen of the Day.</p>
            <p>Shall not the loſt Son be found againe, the Father of theſe that Blaſpheme and are found lyers; But in the eye of our weakeneſſe their proſperitie will weaue the webbe of enuie; murmure not at the
<pb facs="tcp:16312:4"/>good-man of the Houſe; Is it not lawfull; is it no wrong (as he will) to diſpoſe the riches of his owne goodneſſe; nay, rather may we not all ſay, we are vnprofitable, we haue both gon out of the way, there is none that doth good, no not one; nay, are not his Iudgements according to truth; O man grudge not his grace, diſpute not his juſtice.</p>
            <p>But they haue bin, and will be to the worlds end, our perſecutors and ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, need they not ſo much the more our Prayers; recompence no man evill for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; Therefore let the Congregations of the faithfull Pray for them, poore, blind, diſtracted, naked, wretched people, and giue glory to God, who hath done away the vaile from theſe hidden myſteries, that hindred our ſtedfaſt ſight, Though to blinde mindes and deafe harts, this vaile remaines ſtill vntaken away.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16312:5"/>
            <p>Wherein for mine owne part, J chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge little, not ſo much as thoſe that brought to the Tabernacle guifts of their owne ſpinning of Blew and other colours; But rather to be in the number of thoſe ſervants, that drew out the wonderfull Wine for the Bridegroomes Feaſt, to beare it to the Gouernor and the Gueſts; though to cast in my myte with others J was never vnwilling.</p>
            <p>Finally, to thoſe that require a Signe, or thinke this Confidence; Boaſting that high ſtiles are not ſteps for the declining age of this weake world to climbe, my age of this weake world to climbe, my defence is no ſhorter then free.</p>
            <p>Leaſt any ſhould thinke of me aboue or better then he ſeeth me to be, as others to ſuſpect a forged paſſe; To preſent you with Pearles of that ſort or holy things, I forbeare at this time.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16312:5"/>
            <p>If the debt be paid the ſecret of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed oyle is to my ſelfe; Though J ſhut the Doore or ſhadow my name, I feare no faces, ſmiles nor frownes, for, the hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to me no chaines are heauie, it is no bought nor ſtolne fire, my ability nor bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe extending ſo high; yet a Candle too high mounted for Sathan, and all his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to blowe it out, thriued the Goſpell the leſſe, rejected of the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all alike hit not the marke, they preſſe forward, wranglers ſtarted aſide like a broken Bowe, the match is wonne, one Foord is not knowne to all Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; eleven ſtrikes the clocke ſaith he, twelue ſaith ſhe; doe theſe contradict thoſe that are not against vs or with vs; Antichriſtians thoſe that are not against vs, are with vs; Even ſo, glory be to him alone (the Set is ours) the houre and ſet
<pb facs="tcp:16312:6"/>time of whoſe Iudgement is at hand; and O Lord remember thy ſervants <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iacob,</hi> &amp; looke not to the ſtubbornnes, nor to the wickednes of this People, turne their harts, preſerue thy Church, and his victorious Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>. to tread downe the power of his enemies, our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne gratious Lord and the Queene, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint them with thy holy Spirit, Crowne them with Grace; and forren Princes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the Kings excellent Siſter, with a happie life here, and eternall life here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Be gratious to the remnant of <hi>IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEPH,</hi> heare J beſeech thee the Prayer of thy ſervant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Servant of Ieſus Chriſt: O A SVRE DANIEL. DANIEL, — I END AL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Poſtſcript</note>TO maske my name with boldneſſe to vnmaske Error J craue no Pardon, the manner let none diſpiſe; Dreames in times past haue beene interpreted, our Fathers in divers manners haue beene ſpoken vnto, the winde bloweth where it liſteth.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16312:6"/>
            <head>
               <seg rend="mirror">ELEANOR AVDELEY</seg>
               <lb/> REVEALE O DANIEL,
<lb/> TO THE GREAT PRINCE, the King of <hi>Great</hi> BRITAINE, FRANCE, and IRELAND, Defender of the Faith.</head>
            <head>
               <hi>THE INTERPRETATION OF THE VISIONS OF THE PROPHET DANIEL,</hi> revealing the Man of Sinne; And the Morning Starre, before the comming of the Day.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Viſions of this Prophet are revealed the ſame things contained in the Revelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which GOD gaue to Ieſus Chriſt, to ſhew vnto his Servants things which muſt ſhortly come to paſſe; things that are not, to bring to nought things that are: And as he ſignified to his beloved Servant IOHN,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16312:7"/>the Contents of the ſecret Booke by his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell; Even ſo the Lambe ſlaine by the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Decree purpoſed from the foundation of the world; Declared the ſame things to the man greatly beloved, his ſervant DA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIEL, vnfolded in this preſent expoſition; drawing the juice of many ſorts wanting roome and leaſure, to lay things in order, wherein the Scripture will repaire the want of methode. Being not willing for the ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a Match to make a fire, when the ſtroke of a Flint is of more facilitie; Speaking not to a People of a ſtrange Speech and of a hard Language, but to the Houſe of <hi>Iſraell;</hi> Avoyding mans enticing words; things without life, giue no life, that revealeth not the teſtimony of IESUS; at whoſe Name, a name aboue every name, Let every knee bowe. Heare all yee Children of my people, harken O Earth!</p>
            <p>The firſt viſion of this holy Prophet, was in the I. yeare of the raigne of BELSHAZ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZER, King of Babilon; from which ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Babilon takes the denomination. One and Twentie hundred yeares ſince.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16312:7"/>
            <p>Wherein he ſaw the foure Windes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or the loſed Angels bound in the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> the auntient bounds of the great Roman Empire, that ſtroue vpon the great Sea, and the foure great Beaſts, that came vp from the Sea diuers one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Theſe blowing Windes had no power to hurt, till the ſervants of God were Sealed in the foreheads, at what time that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth became a Monarchy, perſecuting the Church of God being then with Child, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing in birth, crying and pained to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered of the man Childe, roaring like a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the whole Forreſt ringing, ruling all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with a Rod of Iron; that breaketh in pieces and ſubdueth all things: He is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> ſo haue the ſervants of God a Two-fold ſence. Beſides man including ſome other of his Creatures, bearing the names of men, yet being neither Man nor Beaſt; Praiſe yee him Sun and Moone, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I heard the number of them: And here ended the Sealing of the firſt Covenant, a yoake which our Fathers were not able to beare, to eſtabliſh the ſecond, which is Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16312:8"/>to put his Lawes in their mindes, with the Penſell of his Grace to write them in their hard harts, a light Burthen, for the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Law, graven in ſtone is the ſentence of death; But the Spirit giveth life to ſtony harts, that were dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes; yea, the whole valley of dead Bodies, turn'd into Stones and Earth, from ABELL the firſt Borne, to the laſt man taken vp in the Field, they are all holy vnto the Lord, their iniquitie is forgiven and forgotten, as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee remembreth their ſinne no more.</p>
            <p>Of theſe were Sealed to bee of the ſeed of ABRAHAM, one hundred forty and foure Thouſand, twelue times twelue Thouſand: Of which faithfull Number IESVS CHRIST the Saviour of the world, the only begotten Sonne of the living GOD, in the likeneſſe of ſinfull Fleſh without Sinne, the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> was ſealed on the Eight day of his Nativitie; The Lyoneſſe bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but one, and but once in her life.</p>
            <p>That with the ſprinckling and ſhedding of his Blood, both Covenants might be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; Theſe were the firſt Fruits vnto God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16312:8"/>and to the Lambe, hauing the Token of the everlaſting Covenant, of the great myſterie in thoſe times, concerning CHRIST and his Church, put in the Fleſh a Figure of the Heart.</p>
            <p>Which firſt Covenant remaines to vs a Patterne of tendernes, not made with hands, the Heart by a mutuall reſpect being now the Cloſet or ſecret part, whereby wee Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles are made the tender Spouſe, the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of God, fellow heires of the vnſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Riches, joyned to Chriſt the head, that in times paſt were the Children of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and wrath, Aliens from the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> Strangers from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of promiſe, having no hope (without God) in the world, are now, who were ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times farre off; of all Nations, Kindreds and Tongues; vncircumciſed Philiſtines, not of his Brethren; not of the Houſe of his Father, By the blood of IESUS CHRIST made nigh members, of his Body, of his Fleſh, and of his Bones; greater loue and felicitie can none expreſſe.</p>
            <p>Of which great myſterie, Hipocrites, next
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16312:9"/>Harlots, whoſe counterfeit beautie deceiues not him, whoſe praiſe is of men, and not of God; falſe Gods, are no partakers; the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Token, being common to both. To aſſure vs of which, receiving the earneſt of his Spirit, that abideth, not crying Maſter; Careſt thou not, that wee periſh; but Abba, Father.</p>
            <p>Thus our tackling loſt without Anchor, to repayre the ruines and weakneſſe of theſe decayed, ſunke weather-tempeſt driven bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes, ſuch Treaſures of Millions expended and beſtowed, what burthen, what prizes, what things God hath prepared to bee the lading of theſe veſſels of honour; Eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, neither hath entred into the hart of man: To which, all the Tranſported affections felt or fained, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed without paines or feare, may ſeeme but light dotage, as Light and Darkneſſe compared, compared with the Crowne and weight of that Eternall bliſſe.</p>
            <p>The Foure windes prepared for an houre, and a day, and a moneth, and a yeare; are the powers of theſe foure great Beaſts; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16312:9"/>their degrees of reſidence; alſo the finall Blaſt is included; The Sea are the Nations of the Earth.</p>
            <p>The beginning and the ending, thus ſaith hee to the Sea: Waues drowning one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſwelling into Mountaines, for glory foaming out your owne ſhame. Saying, haile to the Wood awake, according to your owne vnderſtanding, you haue made Idols and Images, not by my direction, but after the invention of the Craftſman, and haue exalted your hearts and forgotten mee, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my Praiſe to graven Images, and my glory to another for your God, (not ſetting me before your eyes) you haue gotten a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, a falſe Prophet, whom I ſent to proue you; that takes my lawes in his mouth, not of loue, but for ſtrife and envie: Thinkes he to ſay; Lord, Lord, in thy Name wee haue caſt out Divels, Preached, and Baptized; my anſwer is not vnknowne to you both, though you thinke to plead ignorance, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting and diſpiſing the number of my little ones.</p>
            <p>You onely haue I knowne, of all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16312:10"/>of the Earth, whoſe tranſgreſſions doe haſten your Iudgement; Therefore I will puniſh you for your iniquities, you ſhall bee like the Morning Cloud, and the early dew that paſſeth away as the Chaffe that is driven with a ſcattering whirle-winde out of the Flower, as ſmoake out of a Chimney vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing away; And I will bee like a Lyon, as a Leopard by the way I will wayte and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you, and as a Beare that is bereaued of her Whelpes, I will teare the Kall from your harts and devoure you; But to the faithfull I will bee a King, a Saviour; as an Eagle ſtirring vp her Neſt, fluttering over her young, bearing them vpon the wing; So I will preſerue mine inheritance, my Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the Apple of mine eye.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the words of the Firſt, that was like a Lyon, his ſtrength ſhall overcome the reſt, and take their Dominion away, having no number or finite parts expreſſed; the time of whoſe vndeuided Kingdome is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and alwaies; As his yeares haue no end, his Crownes are many; This is the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> having of Fleſh a tender
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16312:10"/>hart; a mans hart was giuen vnto it; The Prince of the Kings of the Earth, the firſt and the laſt; And becauſe he is the roote, and made of the ſeed of DAVID; Hee is here accompted amongſt theſe Beaſts; This is hee that ſate vpon the white Horſe, the Circle of the Earth, to iudge and make War; beholding the Inhabitants like Graſshop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; and a Bowe and a Crowne was giuen vnto him; Hee is the Lord of Lords, the King of Kings, and of his Kingdome there is no end.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Beaſt like a Beare, the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth head, that had Three ribbes in the Mouth betweene the Teeth of it, ſignifying, Three hundred yeares; this is the deuouring Raigne of the Heathen Romaine Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, which laſted ſo long, licked by the Diuell; In the infancie of which Empire, the Sonne of God was Crucified, and the Citie of Ieruſalem deſtroyed, wherein the yearely Sacrifice or feaſt of the Paſſouer was ſolemnized, that in her might be found the Blood of Prophets and Saints, and of all that were ſlaine vpon the Earth, in which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16312:11"/>firſt ſeuentie yeares, the Apoſtles and ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie finiſhed their teſtimony what they had ſeene and heard, after which followed the ouer-ſpreading of abomination ſpoken of by our Sauiour, making the Sanctuary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, defiled with Carkaſſes which can neither ſee, heare, nor walke, abominable carrion, the houſe of Prayer, made the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery of the Diuell, for his deuices to ſtand in.</p>
            <p>And this is hee that ſate vpon the Red Horſe, Hauing a great Sword giuen vnto him, to make Warre with the Church of God, deuouring much Fleſh, Burning, Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching it with fire, Haile mingled with Blood, deſtroying Trees, and all greene graſſe, ſmote euery Herbe, and brake euery Tree; and here ended the firſt Woe with this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Beaſt, all fire and horrible Cruelty, ſuch as there was none like it in all the Land of ſpirituall Egypt ſince it became a Nation, and ſhortly after began the next Woe, where the fire is not mentioned, becauſe the ſmoake is ſo great, thicke darkeneſſe or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, falſe doctrine extinguiſhing the Light of truth, which ſhall continue vntill the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16312:11"/>third Woe, Hell fire, and Brimſtone or Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, iſſuing out of their Mouthes, a great crye from him that ſits vpon the Throne, when Redneſſe ſhall be turn'd into Paleneſſe to the Maide behinde the Mill, the Captaine in the Dongeon, free and bond, becauſe of the laſt Plague the ſecond Death.</p>
            <p>The third Beaſt that was like a Leopard, or halfe a Lyon, an Ape betweene Man and beaſt, whoſe feete or firſt footing, were as the feete of a Beare, that had vpon the back of it foure Wings, like a Fowle or painted Bird: Two of the Eagle, and two of the Dragon; ſignifying his time, Foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares before the comming in of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, then came the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> to Ieruſalem, and beſieged it, taking the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the Night, what Linkes or Torches brought him thither I reade not, but Moon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light there was little, though hee were on his way or Wing, but letted Two hundred yeares before.</p>
            <p>Bearing alſo foure heads, foure ſtanding vp for it, ſhewing the deuiſion of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire into ſo many parts, being then too
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16312:12"/>large and great for the gouernment of one man. This is the Dragon of Egipt; that Monarchy that began with the Chriſtian Emperours, whoſe deadly wound (Death to the Soule) was waſhed in the Blood, and healed by the Stripes of the heauenly Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan; There is now no healing of the Bruiſe, it is putrified, the Wound is grieuous; the Leopard cannot change his ſpots; binde thy Tyre vpon thy head, forbeare to cry: O Virgin daughter of Egipt, in vaine ſhalt thou goe vp into Gillead and take Balme, or vſe Medicines, thou doſt runne in vaine. And this is hee that ſate vpon the blacke Horſe; the Ethiopian cannot change his skinne, leſſe man then the <hi>Minataure;</hi> more Monſter then a <hi>Centaure,</hi> ingendred of black Cloudes, carried about of every Winde, to whom is reſerued the Blackneſſe of Darkneſſe for ever: Blacke will take no other hew; hauing a payre of Ballances gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into his hand, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to meaſure to all men, rich and poore, free and bond, a meaſure of Wheate for a penny, and three meaſures of Barley for a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16312:12"/>penny; Hoe! every one that thirſteth, and hee that hath no money, Come buy and eate, giue not your money for ſtones in ſtead of Bread, ſay not Ignorance is better then Knowledge, Neither hurt the Oyle and the Wine; Touch not a Lords annointed, and doe his Prophets no harme, that Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh you with truth and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>The laſt Beaſt the fourth, that is the Eight, and was Seven heads and is not, and is of the Seven, and goeth into perdition, that had great Iron Teeth, that devoured and brake in peeces, and ſtamped the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due with the feete thereof, and was divers from all the Beaſts that were before it; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Miter of Tenne hornes, ſignifying alſo, though the Crownes be not here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſo many hundred yeares his Limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted time, the Tenne dayes of tribulation in the Apocalips, wherein the Divell ſhall haue power to caſt the faithfull into Priſon; (Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Tribulation imediately of thoſe dayes; Two ſhall be in the field, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Nine of which number are expired, and ſome part of the laſt hundred, but how many are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16312:13"/>to come; by theſe hornes preciſely cannot be aymed at without the Art or Science of Chronologie; This is <hi>Iudas</hi> the Divell, the King of <hi>Babilon</hi> and Egypt, the raigne of Antichriſt Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> count the Letters of his name for it is the nomber of his time, whoſe name is Death; hated mortally of his time, whoſe name is Death; hated mortally the King of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italie:</hi> This is hee that ſate vpon the Pale Horſe, the ſonne of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, of all Complexions the darkeſt, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to corruption, threatning alone, a hart charged with ſo much wickedneſſe and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice as the Red Horſe, all the ſanguines in the Rayne-bow, and the Sword cannot ſet out more of Bruitiſh crueltie; had he winges to his will, and of time length to the height and bigneſſe of his inſatiable minde; NERO, TITVS, DOMITIANVS, theſe beaſts of the Earth, their hearts and policies parraleld would ſeeme but a Curre coupled or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with this greedy Woolfe. A Bull as bloudy as the Beare.</p>
            <p>Whoſe land is covered with Locuſts and Darknes; even darknes that may bee felt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of the depth of the bottomleſſe pit
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16312:13"/>of Sathans malice very grievous; yet had all the faithfull light in their dwellings that they might not looſe the way; for it was Commanded theſe Armies of Scorpions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging the holy City, hauing pernitious ſtings, both wayes voluptuous and maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, The power of the Enemy that they ſhould not hurt the graſſe of the Earth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any greene thing, by any meanes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould hurt them, but only drye Trees or boughs, bearing no fruite of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, thoſe men that haue not the Seale of God in their graceleſſe foreheads, that they ſhould not kill theſe wretched blinde miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable People, but that they ſhould bee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented fiue Moneths, as in thoſe dayes the moſt part, moſt Lamentable in the ſiege of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by Famine were tormented ſo long compaſſed with a Trench, kept in on every ſide, Seeking death, and deſiring to dye, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This did the Lord becauſe the Princes of Egipt, harkened not to milde MOSES; but hardened their harts, and did evill in the ſight of the Lord, after the Abominations of the Heathen; Therefore ſaith the Lord,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16312:14"/>I am againſt thee ô Dragon, which lyeſt in the Hart (the middeſt of the Rivers) which ſaid my Riuers are mine owne, I haue made it for my ſelfe; I will put hookes in thy Clawes, and leaue the Throne into the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, where there is no water; and all the Inhabitants ſhall know that I am the Lord, becauſe they haue beene a ſtaffe of Reede to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they tooke hold of thee by the hand, thou didſt breake and Rent all their ſhoulder, and when they learned on thee, thou brakeſt, and made all their loynes to be at a ſtand, with the Burthens of Bricke and Rubbiſh thy Officers did lay vpon them.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt giuen them Stubble for Straw, vapor of ſmoake for Victuall; thou haſt made their liues bitter vnto them; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord is againſt thee whoſe healed Wound is feſtred, turned wilde againe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Antichriſtian and incureable, thou that haddeſt the Ballances in thine owne hand; Thou that art like a Leopard or a young Lyon of the Nations, as a Dragon; or a Whale in the Seas, with thy Diadem
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16312:14"/>of Ten hornes, crowned with Ten Crowns, ſo many Antichriſtian hundred yeares, Nine of which accompt are caſt, paſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired.</p>
            <p>Troubling the waters with thy feete, and fowleſt their Rivers; the whole Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> the third part of the maine Sea is become Blood; Behold the Lord is againſt thee and againſt thy Rivers, which are turned into Wormwood (woe due O <hi>Rome</hi>) and Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke; Even the Third part of the waters, the ſtreames of Iuſtice and Mercy are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come poyſon and Bitterneſſe; I hate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe your Images, Feaſt dayes, Proceſſions, Solemne aſſemblies, ſaith the Lord; who required thoſe things: I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould runne downe free as water, and Righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtreame; Woe the Bloody Citie.</p>
            <p>You are impudent and diſobedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as the day of your Viſitation, ſo are your ſinnes hidden from you, when you ſhall ſay for ſhame to the Mountaines Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vs, and to the Rocks and Hills fall vpon vs; you will know your tranſgreſſion, the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16312:15"/>long Wings of the morning, the Caues of MAKADAH ſhall not preſerue you, Ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening, Thundring Cannons, the whole Globe at a ſhot, ſhiuering your Bodyes, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your Soules, and making your harts to hop: Eare never heard, neither hath entred into the hart of man ſuch horror, forſaken of all, but the Divell and his Angells, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and buried aliue, of all the Creatures not a drop of water remaining, of Light not a ſparke, Rebells theſe terrors as Shot or Haileſtones from Heaven Pell-mell, ſhall driue you into a Bottomleſſe gulfe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; the great day of his wrath is come, ſaying to the fiery Lake; Hide vs from the face of him that ſits vpon the Throne.</p>
            <p>When the faithfull ſcattered People ſhod with the everlaſting Ghoſpell of Peace, after all their labours and travaile in this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall enter into the Land of Reſt: Here is the Body of the Beaſt deſtroyed; PHAROAH and all his Multitude of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeving Lowzie orders; even all his Hoſt of furious Horſemen as Locuſts, eating e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very herbe, and all the fruite of the Trees
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16312:15"/>the haile had left, drowned in Hell Fyre the bottomleſſe red Sea, that may boaſt rather of their Blaines and Boyles, then Vermin, which their owne Magitians denie not to be the manifeſt finger of God; vaunting they winne by their Coſening game term'd Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, the Ioyes of heaven, and Secret bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Almes in breeding Lice: Such vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane Ragges paſt mending, I did meane to caſt away, but ſince you will not heare MOSES and the Prophets, I will beſtowe ſome labour to ayre them for you, and your patch'd Coates waxen olde and bad to make bags for heavenly Treaſure, well may they ſtoppe Bottles when your Reward is weeping and gnaſhing of Teech; in thoſe dayes, all the Water I finde the Saints will ſupply you with, to coole your bliſtered Tongues.</p>
            <p>Maſters though to ſimple Peoples you ſeeme to make ſtraite ſteps, it is no newes to ſay you incline too much on the left hand. Thinke yee the Crownes like Gold can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue vs; or hayre as the hayre of Women; The vayle of ſhamefaſtneſſe, ſhewing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16312:16"/>ſobriety and ſubiection: Thinke yee thoſe long locks like ſeparited Nazarites, can co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your notted crownes from the Raizer, or hide your pined Bodyes pinch'd of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender like neighing Horſes prepared to the Battaile, It is not vnknowne to vs, the golden Cup, and theſe gilden counterfeit Crownes like falſe Haire to cover Baldneſſe; Both came out of one Furnace: they are yet vnpaid for.</p>
            <p>Though ESAU ſhould lend you Teares, yet ſhall yee come and worſhip before the feet of them, you now diſpiſe and perſecute; There is no bleſſing reſerved, the Mourning day is at hand, the Armour you beare ſhines with the Brotherly affection you beare vs, wee feare not your furie; Go yee Curſed, heere is your farewell, receiue the Portion of Hipocrites, and eate the fruit of Lyes reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and truſting in your owne counterfeit Righteouſneſſe, painted flames, ſuch falſe Coine will not paſſe. Eternall life is free guift purchaſed by Grace; receiue the wages of Sinne; venemous Armies, the power of the Enemie led by the Starre called <hi>Worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16312:16"/>To thoſe that haue not drunke or ſmoak'd out their eyes, as viſible as Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a Lampe fallen from Heaven, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Warre, Famine, with Peſtilent Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie; the fourth part, the whole Chriſtian world infected by that ſtrumpet Hagge <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italie.</hi> Laſtly, the name of his Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was Death, becauſe hee is the laſt, and Hell followed with them with deadly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Raigning till the day of Iudgement, after which hee ſhall ſwimme with his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and bathe in the Lake that burnes with Fire and Brimſtone.</p>
            <p>Theſe three Beaſt ſignified by the great Citie devided into Three parts, ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall perſecutions of the Church vnder great <hi>Babylon,</hi> With a bold ſtroake, the laſt is not drawne in cullours leaſt to the life; the fourth Beaſt (the falſe Prophet, their Popes falleth,) the bitter Starre turning Iudgement into Gaule of Aſpes falne from Heaven, Signifying the loſing of his Keyes, (pride will haue a fall) for which hee was caſt out of the preſence of God: God and Mammon cannot be ſerved together; here
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16312:17"/>hath hee the command of the bottomleſſe Pit, ſmoaking with Hereſie and ignorance; The Keys of the Kingdome of Hell, which truſt ſo much hee boaſteth of, given him by the Dragon the Divell, to deceiue them that dwell vpon the Earth; ſaying in the ſight and opinion of men; Let it be knowne this day, that I haue done all theſe things at thy word; that theſe are thy Keyes; I am thy Apoſtle; and if I be the man of God, let fire come downe from Heaven and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume all thoſe, that obey not my orders, and Lawes; and at what time yee heare the ſound of my Inſtruments; fall downe and worſhip the Image, that I NABVCHANDNE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZAR haue ſet vp, whoſe breath is in my hand, and whole are all my wayes to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie mee; and who ſo falleth not down, &amp;c,</p>
            <p>This <hi>Baals</hi> Prophet the laſt Beaſt, having devoured and broken in peeces the Roman Empire, exerciſing all the power of him whoſe Rome he vſurpeth; the Lord ſaying, I that forme the Light, and create Darkneſſe; I that make Peace, and create evill, I will ſtrengthen the Armies of the King of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16312:17"/>
               <hi>Babilon,</hi> and put my Sword into his hand. But I will breake PHAROAHS Arme, and and he ſhall groane before him, with the groaning of a deadly wounded man; More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts that keepes backe no mans pay.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Babilon</hi> cauſed his Army to ſerue a great ſeruice againſt CHILDRIC King of <hi>Tirus,</hi> euery head was made Bald of his Race, and euery ſhoulder peel'd, yet had hee no wages for his Armie; Therefore the Land of Egypt ſhall bee his for his labour, becauſe they wrought for mee ſaith the Lord; for there ſhall be no more a Prince in Egypt whoſe brightneſſe was Excellent, and the forme thereof terrible to all the world; But rather a painted Image, a Vaſſoll, that the working of the poyſoned Potion in the golden Cup, the myſterie of iniquitie bee not hindred, A baſe Kingdome the baſeſt of all Kingdomes, neither ſhall it exalt it ſelfe any more aboue the Nations; for I will diminiſh them, it ſhall be no more the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the houſe <hi>Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now the ſpoyle of the Land for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16312:18"/>his Armie and the Sword and Ballances in his owne hand to make a prey of mercy and truth, with his Hornes and heeles as wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to warre and weare out the Saints gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into his hand vntill a time and times; and the deviding of times, Three dayes and a halfe Two and fortie Moneths Three yeares and a halfe, halfe the myſticall weeke, vntill the Day of ſudgement; to make Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of euery thing, that no man may buy or ſell without his Marke, marked with his fiends foote; which is his Seale, the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of the Fiſherman that beareth the name of the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>The nomber of his name is then the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a man, which is the nomber of his Age or Dayes, but this is the nomber of his Moneths; Naturall Beaſts not living ſo long, the yeares being not ſo many as the dayes are to few. As one ſaith, the nomber of his Moneths are with the Lord; Alſo halfe the myſticall Weeke is delivered by the ſame meaſure. The latter Six Moneths ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the former Six hundred, making as compleat Fiftie, as Threeſcore make Fiue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16312:18"/>yeares; Here is Wiſdome the counſell of times and ſeaſons revealed, according to the eternall purpoſe, which the wiſedome of the Father put in his owne power, God hath numbred thy Kingdome and finiſhed it, thou art weighed in the ballances, thou ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that boaſteſt of thy wit, and art found wanting graines innumberable, thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is divided, and given to the people of the Saints of the moſt Higheſt, whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is an everlaſting kingdome &amp;c. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him that readeth count this number well, and well marke, the marke of the Beaſt, is the Signet of the Fiſherman, which men take in their right hand, wherewith his Band are branded in the foreheads, and this is the Caractor and colours that diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſheth his Traine-Souldiers from the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Truth.</p>
            <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord to the King of <hi>Babilon,</hi> Antichriſt thy dayes be few, The great day of my wrath is at hand, even for the Elects ſake, and the Soules that reſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Altar, crying for Execution and Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon thee, whoſe Bodyes thou haſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16312:19"/>beheaded, burned and buryed aliue, ſlaine for the Teſtimony they held, the time is ſhortned, thy Biſhoppricke ſhall bee voyde, and become a habitation for Divells; and becauſe thou remembreſt not to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, by ſwift deſtruction thy memorie ſhall be cut off from the Earth, thy Damnation ſlumbreth not, as a theefe in the night, and as a ſnare it ſhall come ſhortly vpon thee; Thou haſt loved curſing, in bleſſing thou haſt not delighted, but as a cloake for Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, ſelling to thy Marchants for money, thoſe foule oyntments to fill thy Bagge, calling and crying from thy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change and darke ſhoppe; if any man Thirſt to commit Whoredom, ſpirituall or carnall, Treaſon, or Murther, let him come to mee and drinke of my Golden Cuppe, Inceſt or Parricide; <hi>Hoc miſterium firmiter profitemur;</hi> what doe yee lacke; wee can ſell you for Gold, Silver, and pretious ſtones, thin Wood, Braſſe, Iron, and Marble, all manner of Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, in Nunneries or Stewes, what will yee giue; Theſe execrable odors, and thy Brazen browed Bulls, caſting flakes of Fire and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16312:19"/>fulminations in the ſight of men from their noyſome Noſtrills and Thundring throates, as with a Garment thou haſt cloathed thy ſelfe, thou haſt robbed mee even of this whole Nation, therefore prepare thy ſelfe thou curſed for everlaſting fire, prepared for the Divell and his Angells, which ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into thy Bowells like water, and ſoake with thine oyntments, as oyle into thy Bones, and mingle with thy marrow; thus let the Enemies of the Lord bee rewarded, yea, in the meane time let them be their own executioners; let one IVDAS with Poyſon burſt out the Bowells of another; let their hope be as the giuing vp of the Ghoſt, and their righteouſneſſe wherein they truſt, in thy remembrance as water that paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; Let them curſe, but Bleſſe thou ô Lord to whom vengeance belongeth, ſhew thy ſelfe, lift vp thy ſelfe thou Iudge of the Earth, and to this proude man of Sinne render a reward; let him not haue the vpper hand, ſitting vpon the Throne of Iniquitie in thy Temple, ſhewing himſelfe that hee is God, Conſume him ô Lord with the Breath of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16312:20"/>thy mouth, and deſtroy him quickly with the Brightneſſe of thy comming.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this Beaſt his habitation is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a woman for Sorceries, ſhameleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and gorgious trimming, arrayed in Purple and Scarlet, the Virgin daughter of the King of <hi>Egipt,</hi> is become the Whore of the King of <hi>Babilon,</hi> the faithfull Citie is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Harlot, hauing in her hand a Cuppe full of abominations, Witchraft and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, viz. worſhipping Idols of Gold and and Silver, Braſſe, Wood, and Stone, mixing holy things with filthy excrements, remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and calling the foule Sinagogue of Sathan, the Church of God, and theſe are the ſpices and ſpirits wherewith her Cup is brewed; and this is the Golden Cuppe wherewith the Kings of the Earth haue been made ſo drunken with, a Cup of <hi>Sodome,</hi> Wine mixed with the Blood of Dragons, and ſtirred with the ſtings of Aſpes; Is this meate indeed, and drinke indeed, the ſawce commeth after; Is this the true Mother; is this the Woman ſhee is taken for, with Eagles wings; her
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16312:20"/>childe caught vp vnto God and to his Throne, and having a crowne of Twelue Starres; in no wiſe in her there is no Bowells of a Mother, though they ſtriue to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Her Iudgement followeth; And a name was written vpon her forehead <hi>BABI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LON,</hi> The Mother of Harlots, and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Earth, the Print is not ſmall, yet not ſo large as the myſterie is deepe; It was written, and therefore to bee read: Thus, the hidden myſtery of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigmaticall writing is here, the ſecret of numbers to teach vs to number her dayes; The numbers are theſe, and I heard the number of them, Two hundred thouſand thouſand horſemen, hauing breaſt plates of fire and Gunpowder or hiacinth, force and furie in ſtead of faith and loue, alluding to the double number of NINVS Horſemen, wherewith he ſubdued ſo many Nations in Seventeene years: The double confirmation of this myſterie ſeventeene hundred yeares alſo, being the limited time fixed to finiſh her warre, which began with the Lambe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16312:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:16312:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16312:22"/>and ended in ſubduing his Saints and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; And as the fiery Army needing no fuell, were to the Army of NINVS, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of Twenty hundred Thouſand, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting a hundred to one, ſo is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the time, when the ſpreading Vine of the Earth, the cluſters of her Grapes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ripe, ſhe ſhall be caſt into the great wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe of the wrath of God. Theſe Tyrants, (here is wiſdome to looke into theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts) ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and eate her fleſh, and burne her with fire; for God hath put it in their hearts to fulfill his will, when <hi>Babylon</hi> the glory of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, ſhall be as <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorah,</hi> the time is neere, the dayes ſhall not bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed.</p>
            <p>The Father of this goodly Baby, (yet auncient, no novice in her whoredome) for ſo hee nameth himſelfe, there is no need to name him (at whoſe entrance the Fourth Angell or Winde was looſed) as hee is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently notorious, ſo is he miſtaken Sathan that old Serpent, begetting the Impe of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, before ever the Beaſt and his falſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16312:22"/>ſpouſe came together, deceivers as ſeldome wanting cloakes of craft to hide their ſhame, as their of-ſpring faile in Lyneaments and likeneſſe too their Parents, ſeven heads no leſſe markes then Mountaines, ſeeing as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible as ſuperfluous and monſtrous, were it not the Evidence and demonſtration of that Sinagogue to proue her title and viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, drunken with the Blood of Saints and Martyrs, In ſteed of her Mothers milke and breaſt ſhee ſucks her hart-Blood, whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was a Lyer and a Murtherer from the beginning.</p>
            <p>To Adminiſter the rites of their vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous miſtery; This City Bab, hath Citie Goſſips, NINEVY is not invited; ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented at the Preaching of the poore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſhee is none of them; But <hi>Babylon</hi> for her Pride and impudency at this Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſolemnity or ſhew of Chriſtianitie; The Mother of Harlots; for her ſtiffe neck is preferred before her, whoſe name this ſhameleſſe place, never to be outworne or blotten out, beares in her fatall brazen forehead.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:16312:23"/>
            <p>Beſides, this Lady ſitting vpon her Beaſt, ſeventeene Kings to beare vp her Traine, decked with Gold and pretious Stones, and Pearle, whoſe name is alſo <hi>Semiramis</hi> or <hi>Ieſabell,</hi> for magnificence millions of men, viz. a hundred times Twenty hundred Thouſand; Her Altars, Images, Sorceries, and Blood of Prophets and Saints, Saying in her hart, I ſit a Queene and am no Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow; a Lady for ever, I am, and none elſe beſides mee; there are Seven Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Fiue are fallen downe dead drunke, vpon whom the Lord hath poured out the ſpirit of deepe ſleepe, and cloſed their eyes, they ſhall revert nor riſe no more; After ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering the other Two, (though they haue falne from the truth,) ſhall ſtagger and come to themſelues againe; and that Muſt now growne ſower and ſtale, their luſt ſhall be little to taſte thereof againe; The firſt Kingdome or ONE IS, are the Brittiſh Iſlands, the right Inheritance of King IAMES the firſt of that Name of Great <hi>Britaine</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> for the Iles feared the Iudgement of the Lord and ſaw it; Even
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16312:23"/>the ends of the Earth were afraid and drew neere. The other is not yet come, and when it commeth, it can continue no long ſpace, the end of the world is ſo neere.</p>
            <p>O ſenceleſſe poore Beaſts who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched you; why lye yee ſtill, who hath bitten you; ariſe, chooſe not Death rather then life; how are yee ſwolne, why ſhould your Carcaſſes be dung, and meate for the fowles of Heaven? Why will yee dye, ſtand vp; why goe yee backward; what aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is this that hath taken you; be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, vnderſtand, halt not, yet heare the word of the Lord; curſt cattell, backſliding Heifers hee delighteth in Mercy; provoke not him with your ſtrange vanities and Bruitiſh abominations; The day of the Lord is at hand.</p>
            <p>Therefore awake yee Drunkards, weepe and howle all yee drinkers of Wine, becauſe of the new Wine the Deepe Cup, the day of the wrath of the Lord is at hand; yee Kings of the Earth and Rulers of <hi>Sodome,</hi> who haue commited fornication, and lived deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly with this indulgent Witch, the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16312:24"/>mother of Harlots; when yee ſee her brought to the ſtake and vtterly burnt with fire; how will yee ſtand, for ſtrong is the Lord who Iudgeth her; what will yee ſay; yee ſhall ſtand a farre off, or wiſh in vaine the Mountaines to cover you, howling and gnaſhing your Teethes for feare of her Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſo ſinnes as the ſmoake of her Burning haue reached vp vnto Heaven; ſaying alaſſe, alaſſe, <hi>Sodome,</hi> alaſſe, <hi>Babylon, Rome</hi> the great Citie, the head of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; for in the twinckling of an eye, an houre vnlookt for, thy Iudgement is come, is that a time to caſt duſt on your heads?</p>
            <p>Never more ſhall we heare in thee the voyce of Harpers and Pipers, awaking and calling for rewards to Saints and our Lady; and Trumpeters when wee doe our Almes; Never more ſhall wee ſee in thee Idolls or Images ſo auntient, the curious device of the Craftſ-man, nor the ſound of the grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Milſtone; our Altars decked as a ſhop, ſhining with the light of ſo many Tapers and Candles. Nor the voyce of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, called the head, and the Bride by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16312:24"/>Prelates and ſo many Kings our holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; The Net is ſpread, ſhee is taken in the Snare, in grinding the face of the Poore, ſhee that ſo much glorified her ſelfe, in a day and an houre her Plague is come.</p>
            <p>The Thrones of theſe Earthly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes caſt downe the auncient of dayes ſhall appeare; his long Traine, and the great white Throne whereon he ſate, from whoſe Face the Earth and the Heavens vncleane in his ſight fled away, in whoſe preſence mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred Thouſand thouſands, and Ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times Tenne Thouſands; alſo the Two Witneſſes are brought forth, the Books of the Law and the Prophets, to Iudge eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man by his workes, or according to his faith, for if they beleeue not the writings of MOSES; how can they beleeue his words of whom MOSES wrote, Theſe Bookes ſhall accuſe them, the witneſſes which God the Father beareth of his Sonne; The other Booke is the Booke of Life, written with the names of Saints that ſhall liue for ever; To whom the iuſt Iudge ſhall deliver the poſſeſſion of that Kingdome that ſhall never
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16312:25"/>paſſe away to be deſtroyed, but remaineth for ever, even for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>The foule Beaſt, ſome of his purtenances will be wanting, if his hornes be not farther Conſidered; foure came vp out of the North part of his head, the French Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; of the South ſide ſixe Spaniſh; before whom, there were Three of the firſt, their Race pluckt vp by the Rootes; amongſt theſe came vp an other little Horne about the midſt of the time: in this Horne were eyes, like the eyes of a man, in workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſtriuing to ſet Nature a patterne; curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in all Arts, and doing honour to vertue, but wanting the gift of grace, opened a fearefull Mouth; the King of the Eaſt, whoſe looke is more ſtout then the higheſt of his fellow Hornes.</p>
            <p>Hitherto is the end of the matter of theſe earthly Monarchies, and the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath beene alſo declared the matter of the end: The Story is yet but chalked out, Therefore in theſe following Viſions is contained more at large, the occurrence of theoſe dayes before mentioned, even to the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16312:25"/>end of the world; Wherein my deſire is, not as hee that rowleth a ſtone to returne vpon himſelfe, but to make it a twiſted Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Cord, to draw vp the weight that preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſo hard of infidelitie.</p>
            <p>The Prophet beheld till the auncient of dayes did ſit to Iudge the quicke and the dead, and the Beaſt caſt aliue into the Lake Fire, his Body deſtroyed and given to the Burning flame, to be tormented day and night, for ever and ever.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>DANIEL.</hi> CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>IN the third yeare of BELSHAZZER a Viſion appeared vnto DANIEL alone, even to himſelfe, and hee heard a mans voyce that called, ſaying; GABRIEL, make the man vnderſtand the Viſion; ſo he came neere vnto him, and ſaid; O Sonne of man, the time of this Viſion extends to the end of all things; behold therefore I will make thee know what ſhall come to paſſe, euen to the laſt day, the great day of Wrath
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16312:26"/>and Indignation, for at the time appointed the end ſhall be.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>MEDES AND PERSIANS</item>
                  <item>THE ROVGHE GOATE.</item>
                  <item>SEND MEE SPANIARDS</item>
                  <item>THE GOTHE ROAGVE.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt matter giuen him to vanderſtand, is the breaking in peeces of the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, which ſpiritually is called <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Egipt;</hi> where alſo the members of our Lords Body are Crucified, ſignified by the Ram, the Hee Goate is the <hi>Turke;</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours the Two hornes in the Eaſt and Weſt, are alſo ſignified by the Kings of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> and <hi>Perſia.</hi> The foure Kingdomes ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp out of that Nation, are the Iſles of Great <hi>Britaine, France, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Turky.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, the Goate himſelfe ſhall be hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a King of a fierce Countenance, not regarding the perſon of the old, nor ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fauour to the young, caſting downe ſome of the hoaſt of PHAROAH, and of the Starres to the ground: For the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion againſt the daily Sacrifice was the Hoaſt given over: A King vnderſtanding darke ſentences which are ſome part of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16312:26"/>holy Scriptures, through policie and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wiſdome, he ſhall cauſe the craft of the Divell to proſper, for by Peace and affected pittie, and ſatisfying the ambitious mindes of ſome Chriſtians, he ſhall not only draw them to denie the faith, but many others following their example: Not by his owne power, but by the Divells policie he ſhall be mighty, whoſe looke is more ſtout then his fellowes, But by the great day of the Lord, he ſhall be broken without hand.</p>
               <p>Now in thoſe dayes, when the Goate was come cloſe vnto the Ramme, and had caſt him downe and ſtamped vpon him; The Prophet that beheld as by a perſpectiue theſe remote things, heard alſo one Saint ſpeaking, and an other Saint ſaid vnto that certaine Saint that ſpoke, how long is the time for this Viſion to the end of the world, that the holy Citie of God, and his choſen People be no longer trodden vnder foote; And hee ſaid vnto mee vnto Two Thouſand Three hundred dayes; Then ſhall the Sanctuarie bee cleanſed, and the holy People Iuſtified.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16312:27"/>
               <p>The dayes bee ſo many yeares to the end of the world, beginning at the Viſion, which was about the yeare of the world, 342.5.</p>
               <p>Of the certaine Saints ſpeaking, or the nomber of wonderfull ſecrets, I omit to ſpeake, that to the moſt part might appeare (being in this Land, and theſe late dayes) but ſome tale of a Phenix, though to bee te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified of more then fiue hundred men and women beſides my ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>DANIEL.</hi> CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>AFter theſe Viſions in the firſt yeare of DARIVS the Son of AHASHV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ERVS, the Prophet vnderſtood by Bookes and Computations, the nomber of yeares whereof the world of the Lord came to IEREMIAH the Prophet, concerning the deſolation of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that ſeventie yeares ſhould be accompliſhed; And whilſt hee was ſpeaking in Prayer, and preſenting his ſupplication before the Lord for the holy
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16312:27"/>Mountaine the People of God, euen for the holy Citie the Church, that to the end of the world muſt be trodden vnder foote, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that ruinons place the Citie of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> is a figure trodden downe at this day. Yet was this <hi>Hebron</hi> built ſeaven yeares before <hi>Zoan</hi> in <hi>Egipt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The man <hi>GABRIEL</hi> which was cauſed to flie ſwiftly, touched him and ſaid (allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the former matter of his ſtudie and meditations, as of troublous, appetites, and Cogitations ſomtimes Dreames are deriued) O DANIEL I am come vnto thee againe to giue thee more skill and vnderſtanding; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentie weekes are determined vpon the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citie, ſignifying the time, not onely when the Sonne of God by his ſuffering ſhould make reconciliation for ſinne, but a time and times and part of time, three dayes and a halfe, halfe the myſticall Weeke, to make an end of Sinnes to finiſh tranſgreſſion, and to make a new Heaven and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth everlaſting righteouſneſſe to ſeale vp the Viſions and Prophecies with the Seale of aſſurance, that all theſe things
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16312:28"/>are paſt and true, and to annoint the moſt holy King and Kings, and Lord and Lords, the firſt and the laſt.</p>
               <p>And here againe the Angell GABRIEL willeth him to know and vnderſtand the things of which he ſhall informe him; The firſt is this, that from the going forth of the Commandement, which is the beginning of the Creation to the building of the new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, the ſecond comming of <hi>Meſsiah</hi> the Prince the Sonne of God, it ſhall be Seaven Weekes or Seaven Moneths, as it is ſpoken by EZEKIEL the Prophet; Then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Citie the Sanctuary ſhall be walled in, in a troublous time, to make a ſeperation betweene the Sanctuary and the Prophane place.</p>
               <p>And in the middeſt of this Propheticall weeke, after Threeſcore and Two weekes, <hi>Meſsiah</hi> ſhalbe cut off, the Son of God ſalbe Crucified and be deliuered vnto the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp; they ſhal ſcourge him &amp; put him to death, the People of the Prince (for it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the <hi>Iewes</hi> to put any man to Death) theſe People the <hi>Roman</hi> Nation ſhall deſtroy
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16312:28"/>the Citie of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and the Sanctuary; at the end of which Warre there ſhall begin a floud of Fyre (kindled in our Saviours dayes) during the Raigne of thoſe Ethnick Beares; and the abomination of deſolation ſtanding where it ought not; then let him that is in <hi>Iudea</hi> flye to the wilde Mountaines for ſafety; for in thoſe times Iudgement did begin at the houſe of God; and if firſt Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice did begin at his Children and Servants in this life, what ſhall the end bee of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, whom hee hates in the world to come, that haue not obeyed the Goſpell of God.</p>
               <p>Theſe Flouds the Serpent will caſt out of his Mouth, a time and times &amp; halfe a Time, to trie them of the holy Covenant, their boldneſſe, what confidence they haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords oath, and whether they will perſeuer in this holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe all their dayes to their liues end, and not rather feare his power, who is Sathan the Prince of this world, or at leaſt the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious cruell hands of his torturing Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:16312:29"/>
               <p>Whoſe liues cannot ſatisfie their malice; for had not the ſenſeleſſe earth ſhewed more pitty then they, opening her Mouth to helpe theſe poore outcaſts, their torments had beene endleſſe; Sooner they may ſwim, and ſinke in their Blood, then daunt or foyle their courage, not abaſhed for their Boaſts, threats, nor fiery Bands they feare them not at all; their Triumphs are graven vpon the Palmes of the Lords hands, hee forgets them no more, then a Mother forgets her new-borne Sonne, her ſucking childe, when the Tongue cleaues to the roofe of the Mouth for Thirſt, to haue compaſſion on him; be of good cheere, you haue peace in Chriſt, though tribulation in this world; perſecutions are but like the Trauell of a Woman, who hath ſorrow becauſe her houre is come, but as ſoone as ſhee is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of the Childe, ſhee remembreth no more the anguiſh, for ioy a man-childe is borne into the world.</p>
               <p>The Lambe, the Bread of life ſhall feede them, they ſhall hunger nor thirſt no more; hee ſhall wipe all Teares from the eyes of his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:16312:29"/>Children; theſe vilde Bodyes, ſubiect to all infirmities, ſhall then be made like his owne glorified Body, of more perfection then our firſt Parents, a living Soule that ſhall not dye to Sinne; neither ſhall the heate of the Sunne ſmite them; for hee ſhall haue mercy vpon them, and leade them to liuing Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of truth, cleere as Chriſtall; theſe that come to him, or overcome the world, hunger no more, they haue reſt and peace for paine, and by their white Robes and Palmes in their hands, the Enſignes of peace and victorie; they ſhall be knowne, neither to be Heretiques or Schiſmatiques, but his ſervants that haue fought for his Kingdome that it ſhould not be delivered vp vnto An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</p>
               <p>The followers of him, who ſhall ſhortly tread theſe Traitors in the great Wine-preſſe of the wrath of God, who haue turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Eares from the wholſome Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Leaues of which are for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Nations, that they might be rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with the Prophane fables of Drunken doting old wiues.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:16312:30"/>
               <p>But with all the faithfull the Lord ſhall confirme his truth and Covenant for a Weeke from the beginning of the world vntill the laſt end thereof; This week is Seven thouſand yeares, conſiſting of yeares, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths and weekes; finiſhed when the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world, are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of our Lord, and of his Chriſt, and hee ſhall Raigne for ever and ever: When the Tenth part of the Citie fell, the Tenne dayes of Tribulation are ended; Seven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand names of men ſlaine in the great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, <hi>Dies Solis, Dies Lunae, Dies Martis, Dies Mercurij, Dies Iovis, Dies Veneris, Dies Saturni;</hi> the remnant were affrighted, and gaue glory vnto the God of Heaven.</p>
               <p>For wee muſt not be ignorant of this one thing, that one day with the Lord is as a Thouſand yeare, and a Thouſand yeare as one day; In the middeſt of which Weeke, the Lord ſhall cauſe the oblation and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to ceaſe, ſaying, Sacrifice and Offering thou wouldeſt not, but a Body haſt thou prepared mee without ſpot, for the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the tranſgreſſions that were vnder
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16312:30"/>the firſt Teſtament. The Blood of which firſt Teſtament of Beaſts, God enioyned to purifie the patternes of heavenly things, the Veſſels of the Miniſtrie, but the heavenly things themſelues with better Sacrifices (which are the Conſciences to purge them from dead workes, that they may be cleane veſſels to ſerue the living God.)</p>
               <p>Thus hee once ſuffered, the vncreated in likeneſſe of a Creature like feeble ſinfull fleſh, ſowne in weakeneſſe and diſhonour in the Duſt, but raiſed in Power &amp; the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Fathers. Glory, the expreſſe Image of his perſon, over whoſe excellent Nature, voyd of violence and deceit, the Graue could get no victory, no more then the wombe can keepe backe a ſonne at the time of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, redeemed from the Bowels of the Earth, and ranſomed by the riches of his owne vnſearchable Treaſure and quickning Spirit.</p>
               <p>This ſeeming vgly Serpent, rather ſome ſhadow or his skin, at whoſe approach men turne pale and quake more terrified then hurt; But rocking Babes the faithfull a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16312:31"/>ſleepe, others run raving with ſtaring fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie for feare, as if this once appointed ſo were fits to be chaſed away, not calling to minde the Reſurrection of IESVS CHRIST, hath opened his Iawes, his Sting cut out and nayled to the Croſſe, that bold Champion ſcorning to be his executioner, ſetting his victorious foot vpon the Traytors head, by ſpirituall alliance kinne to the Divell, proud of advantage, bites the Heele of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our with his rotten Teeth, for want of his Poyſoned ſting.</p>
               <p>But heare ô Death vnſtop thine Adders eares from whoſe Mole-ſighted eyes, the light of Repentance is hid, behold thy time and Plague is at hand; thy pined crying Priſoners, thou ſhall reſtraine their libertie no longer, that ſay our Bones are dryed and our hope is loſt, when ſhall we dwell in the Land of the living; behold, thy Caues and Caſtles ſhall be deſtroyed &amp; broken downe, and the Earth that opened her Mouth and ſwallowed vp the Flood ſhall caſt it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the twinkling of an Eye, thou ſhalt giue vp thy accompts, for of the Sonnes and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:16312:31"/>Daughters of the Lord, thou ſhalt not keepe backe ſo much as the leaſt, whoſe names are written in the Booke of life.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, Viper, ſeed of the olde Serpent, thy ſentence is for that bold attempt; Fuller of malice then hurt, thy houſe ſhall be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with vnquenchable Fire, the Place ſowne with vnſauory poyſoned Salt, and thy Carrion-carkaſſe ſwallowed vp of thine owne Brood the ſecond Death.</p>
               <p>All which myſticall Weeke or Seaven Moneths formerly mentioned, as it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Prophet EZECHIEL; The Land of <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſhalbe burying of <hi>Gog</hi> that Sathan, that the Land may be cleanſed.</p>
               <p>Hitherto are the matters talked of between the man GABRIEL and the Prophet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>DANIEL.</hi> CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>IN the third yeare of CYRVS King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> a thing was revealed to DANIEL (whoſe name was called BELTESHAZ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZER) and the thing was true but the time
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16312:32"/>appointed was long. Theſe are the things not only come to paſſe, in this latter age of the world, but at this time and in this day; ſignified by the Son of God to the Prophet.</p>
               <p>PRINCE OF PERSIA. — I CAN POPE FRIERS.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Divell.</note>
                     <hi>I can Pope Friers. Man hold vp my Traine?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Pope.</note>
                     <hi>Kings I Depoſe, and all their Race, to Raigne.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Divell.</note>
                     <hi>And Popes to Friers I can turne againe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Prince of the Kingdome of <hi>Perſia,</hi> (that Lord by whom the Lord of Lords was withſtood,) is Sathan the Divell, MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHAEL one of the firſt Princes that came then to helpe him; This is IAMES King of Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> and the man who is raiſed on high: The one and Twenty dayes; the Lord making no forfeiture, are ſo many Hundred yeares, beginning at the Viſion, and ending this preſent, 1600. And ſo long the words of this Viſion haue been cloſed &amp; ſealed vp; Even till now the time of the end.</p>
               <p>This moſt Bleſſed perſon the Saviour of the world, remained with the Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors (ſignified ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16312:32"/>DANIEL being the preſent Monarchy) till there aroſe vp a new King in <hi>Egipt</hi> which knew not IOSEPH, and ſaid vnto his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Behold, the People of the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> are more, and mightier then wee; Therfore ſet over the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Taskmaſters to afflict them with Burthens, but the more they did afflict them, the more they multiplied and grew. Theſe Kings placed in the higheſt Thrones, to walke in his Statutes to execute his Iudgements, but becauſe they gaue more Eare, and harkened rather to falſe Prophets then to ELIAS and MOSES, for ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and meekneſſe; Repreſenting the Law and the Goſpell, ſuffering their Bodies to lye dead in the ſtreets in an vnknowne Tongue, even hee the Lord departed from them; and with the ſword of his Mouth will fight with their Prince Sathan, renewing alwayes his old quarrell againſt the Church of God.</p>
               <p>And here theſe Kings forſaken of IESVS CHRIST, for one ſecret friend which is the Divell, they haue two open Enemies, the <hi>Turke</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> making their Crownes his footſtoole, this did not CAESAR, by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:16312:33"/>theſe Three the Empire being devided, what can remaine but the bare Image; or the Image of the Picture of him, whoſe deadly wound was healed: Bearing at this day, as Thunder goes before Lightning, for their fatall device, the ſad Fowle blazoned with the ominous Colours of the blacke Horſe; for feare, but halfe diſplaying her wings, in ſtead of her beake ſhee caſts her heads, the Eagle hath Mued her Feathers; Though thou exalt thy ſelfe as the Eagle, and though thou ſet thy neaſt amongſt the Starres, thence will I bring thee downe ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>Theſe things hitherto mentioned concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the laſt Viſion is the preamble for this that followeth, for here the Sonne of God whoſe eyes were like a flame of fire; and his feet like fine braſſe, ſaith he will ſhew vnto the man greatly beloued, that which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Scripture of truth, which is the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> the ſayings of which are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true, that there is none, or but one, that holdeth with him in theſe things, which is the true Interpretation of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:16312:33"/>but MICHAEL our Prince of Great <hi>Britaine</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> that fights and contends with the Enemies of the Lord, about his Body, diſputing with them, haue tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated &amp; changed the truth of God into a lye, worſhipping and ſerving the Creature more then the Creator, for which cauſe God gaue them vp, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now followeth that that is noted in the Scripture of that Prince. After the Temple of God was opened in Heaven, wherein was ſeene the Arke of his Teſtament, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid round about with gold, wherein was the golden Pot that had Manna, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RONS Rodde that budded, and the Tables of the Covenant, And over it the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins of glory, covering the Mercy-Seate, and Lightnings and voyces, and Thunders, &amp;c. This is the Millitant Church that brought foorth the Man-childe, the word of God, caught vp vnto God, and to his Throne, after which the Woman fled into the Wilderneſſe, where ſhee was fed A thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred and threeſcore dayes, which are ſo many yeares.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:16312:34"/>
               <p>The firſt accompt beginneth from the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of deſolation, did ſtand in the Holy place, the yeares being the ſame ſpoken in the laſt Viſion of the Prophet DANIEL, though thirty yeares be taken away, becauſe the Court without the Temple was left out, given vnto the Gentiles, for the Raigne of the firſt Chriſtian Emperour.</p>
               <p>Theſe yeares doe reach to the dayes of thoſe bleſſed Men, when the light of the Goſpell did firſt begin to ſhine, after the great Miſt, laſting a Thouſand two hundred and ninetie yeares, dayes of darkneſſe and gloomineſſe of Cloudes, and thicke Miſts, when the third part of the Sunne was ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and the third part of the Moone, and the third part of the Starres, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable; After theſe dayes were paſt, there was warre in Heaven, MICHAEL and his Angells, fought againſt the Dragon, and the Dragon fought, and his Angells the Ieſuites, and prevailed not, neither was their place found any more in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Heaven is here taken in this place for the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:16312:34"/>Church of God, the fray is fought by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds, by MICHAEL is meant King IAMES; The Dragon needs little expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, It is the Pope, for MICHAEL over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came by the blood of the Lambe, and by the teſtimony of ſo many Biſhops, and other faithfull, crowned with the Glory of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome; Therefore reioyce yee Church of God, yee Congregations of the faithfull, and ye Profeſſors that dwell amongſt them, and woe to the Earth and to the Sea, the Congregation of that Sinagogue the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> Sathans ſeate, where Sathan dwelleth, for the Pope, the Dragon, the Divell is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, having great wrath, becauſe he knoweth he hath but a ſhort time, two woes are paſt, and behold the third woe commeth ſhortly.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed are the Dead that dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their works follow them, and this is the truth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Scripture of Truth, of MICHAEL, And God make the name and Throne, of the King his Sonne, better, and greater then his.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:16312:35"/>
               <p>Though I owe no defence for the name of an Angell given to a Mortall man (in this Propheſie) yet to ſatisfie as well the Envious as the Ignorant, they ſhall finde the Sonne of God ſometimes called by the name of the firſt ADAM, DAVID who ſhall feede his Flocke like a Shepheard, and gather his Lambes with his arme, and carry them in his boſome, ſtiled a man after Gods owne Hart; and in another place from his owne Mouth, holding it no derogation to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, to apply to himſelfe by Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the properties of an auſtere Maſter, a Cruell vſurer, or the vniuſt Iudge, May by the ſame Authoritie giue the name of MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHAEL, or like vnto God in ſome reſpects vnto this Prince who fought the battell of the Lord, more like an Angell then a Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Man; as to the other the name of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, becauſe he ſpake as a Dragon.</p>
               <p>As this young Dragon hath acted his part, his Syer or Damme the old Dragon, his markes may not be forgotten, whoſe Hornes haue beene formerly mentioned in a Miter and Diadem, his ſeaven Heads are ſo many
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16312:35"/>Rulers, as it were Husbands or ſeverall ſorts of Magiſtracy, governing that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the ſeaven Crownes are ſeaven Hundreth yeares, beeing the time from <hi>Romes</hi> foundation to the firſt Emperour. <hi>Equaeua polo, Eterna, Antiqua, Caput Mundi, Celſa. Deum locus. Coeleſtis.</hi> Names of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>DANIEL.</hi> CHAP. XI. DARIVS THE MED. — I DREAMED THVS.</head>
               <p>BEſides this Prince of victorious and bleſſed memory, who came to helpe the King of Kings, that ſate vpon the white Horſe, whoſe name is the word of God, to fight the Battell in Heaven againſt the Prince of the Kingdome of <hi>Perſia,</hi> here is an other of like happy memory, that hath the Honour to haue his name Recorded in this holy antient Prophecie, CONSTANTINE the Great, named, DARIVS the <hi>Mede,</hi> raigning thirtie yeares. In the firſt times of which renowmed Monarchy the Lord
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16312:36"/>ſtood to confirme and ſtrengthen him Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whoſe time three Kings ſtood vp toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>Perſia,</hi> dividing the Empire, which breach, made way for the fourth, the fourth Beaſt, corrupted with Riches and libertie; Farre richer then they all, By whoſe ſtrength through his riches, Chriſtian Princes were ſtirred vp againſt MAHOMET, growing not a little great by their ruines.</p>
               <p>And a mighty King ſhall ſtand vp, the great King of <hi>Tyre,</hi> the abſolute Monarch thereof, and all the dependences North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that ſhall rule with great dominion, and doe according to his owne will, and when hee ſhall ſtand vp the fundamentall Lawes of his Kingdome ſhall bee broken and infringed; And the Kingdome ſhall be divided towards the foure windes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and not to his poſterity, nor according to his Dominion which hee ruled, for this Kingdome ſhall be pluckt vp, even for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, beſides thoſe that were planted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; his naturall ſubiects by a diſpenſation being freed from their oath of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:16312:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caroli Magni Chriſtianiſsimi Romanorum Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoris Corpus hoc conditum eſt ſepulchro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this the King of the South was ſtrong, and he was ſtrong aboue the King of the North, and he had dominion, and his Dominion is a great dominion.</p>
               <p>Theſe two Kings, the King of the North, and the King of the South parting the ten Hornes, the Princes of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia;</hi> In the end of yeares they ſhall ioyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together, for the Kings Daughter of the South ſhall come to the King of the North to make an agreement, but ſhee ſhall not retaine the power of the Arme, neither ſhall he ſtand nor his Arme, or they ſhall be Childleſſe, and ſhe ſhall be given vp, And they that brought her ſent away deſtitute of a Father, and for ſaken of her Brother.</p>
               <p>But out of a branch of her rootes, which are her Father and her Mother, ſignifying their Inceſtuous Mariages, One ſhall ſtand vp in his Eſtate very hardy, and ſhall come with an Armie, and ſhall enter into the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:16312:37"/>fortreſſe of the King of the North, or the King of <hi>Tyre,</hi> and deale againſt them and prevaile; And ſhall carry Captiues into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,</hi> their Gods and their Prnices, and with their Pretious Veſſells of Silver and Gold, and hee ſhall continue more yeares then the King of the North in the Monarchy; So the King of the South, or the King of <hi>Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia</hi> ſhall returne into his owne Land, the Land of Duſt and Aſhes, where his worſt Enemies doe not envie his quiet poſſeſſion: But his Sonnes who ſucceeded each other in the Monarchy, ſhall be ſtirred vp againſt the King of the North, and ſhall aſſemble a great multitude of Forces, and one of them ſhall certainly come and overflow with a floud of Fury, and ſhall paſſe through, and prevaile againſt them of the Holy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; but after that hee ſhall returne and be ſtirred vp, even to his Fortreſſe or beſt Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced place by them.</p>
               <p>And the King of the South, or one of theſe Brothers ſhall be provoked with Chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and ſhall come forth and fight with the King of the North, who ſhall ſet forth a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:16312:37"/>great multitude, but the multitude ſhall bee given into the hands of his Enemies, and himſelfe ſhall be his Priſoner carried a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue into <hi>Ethiopia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when the King of the South, or this <hi>Perſian</hi> King hath taken away the multitude, his heart ſhall be lifted vp againſt God; and he ſhall caſt downe many of his ſervants Tenne Thouſands; but neither hee nor thoſe that come after ſhall bee ſtrengthened thereby.</p>
               <p>(For at the end of Yeares, which are now expired, there ſhall certainely come a King of the North, and hee ſhall ſet forth a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude greater then the former, a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and with much riches, and hee ſhall doe according to his owne will, &amp;c.)</p>
               <p>And in thoſe former dayes there ſhall many ſtand vp againſt the King of the South; alſo the Robbers of the Chriſtians, theſe Extortioners ſhall exalt themſelues, to eſtabliſh the Viſion of the Prophets, and the Figures of the Law, which Prophecied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till IOHN; for the firſt things that are but ſhadowes, are now vaniſhed away, to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:16312:38"/>eſtabliſh the ſecond, but they ſhall fall, So the King of the North ſhall come and caſt vp a Mount, and take the moſt fenced Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and the Armes of the South ſhall not withſtand, neither his choſen People, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall there bee any ſtrength to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, But hee that commeth againſt him, ſhall doe according to his owne will, and none ſhall ſtand before him; and hee ſhall ſtand in the glorious Land which by him ſhall be conſumed; Hee ſhall alſo ſet his face to enter with the ſtrength of his whole Kingdome, and vpright ones with him; thus ſhall hee doe.</p>
               <p>And hee ſhall giue him the Daughter of Women, or a Queene by decent, whoſe Royall blood was corrupted, and ſtayned by the vſurping authority of a Tyranous Husband, but ſhe ſhall not ſtand on his ſide, neither before him, for hee dying ſhee was brought home, and ſhortly after Married to another,</p>
               <p>After which agreement diſſolued, and the League broken, his Succeſſor ſhall turne his face vnto the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Iles, and ſhall take
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:16312:38"/>many Priſoners, but a Prince for his owne behalfe, rather then the honour of God of a happy daring ſhall cauſe the reproach offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ceaſe without his owne reproach, hee cauſed the ſhame to turne vpon him that oppoſeth and exalteth himſelfe aboue all that is called God. The Lord ſometimes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the remedy before the ſore, as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Phyſitians haue Drugs in ſtore for all diſeaſes, preparing the diſobedience of VA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STHI, and the vnlawfull divorce, for the preſervation of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> to hang proud HAMMON and all his wicked Sonnes, ſo this Prince throwing vnder foote his Cappe of Maintenance (whoſe viſage was vnmask'd, by a Munke not long before) thoſe <hi>Babel</hi> Monaſteries, vnmeete Cages for ſuch Craignes, Oſtriges, and chanting Owles, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting not only all the thorney. Choaking Hereſie of falſe Prophets, but the ruſty Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory fictions of Heathen Poets, The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of theſe vncleane and hatefull birds, Though as the eating of doung I loathe them in my Mouth, yet ſince our Saviour and Lord himſelfe vouchſafed to caſt his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:16312:39"/>Eye towards thoſe ſecret privie places, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vs take heed of their Deſerts, I may not ſtop my Noſe or Mouth for niceneſſe, but rather thinke it my part to empty ſuch hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of office, it weakeneſſe did not prevent and hinder my willingneſſe.</p>
               <p>Yet with mine owne hand according to my might (God willing) I will throw one ſtone at this <hi>Thracian</hi> Witch, the wicked Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; If I cannot breake his head, I will breake his Harpe if I can, before hee paſſe headlong downe to Hell the ſtreame: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will omit her Holineſſe (though her natiue Soile and Sex may challenge ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour) how they ſhall walke then, Inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hand in hand togither; And as certaine of their owne Poets mention, her vntimely Death, ſtung by the falſe Scorpion, that lurk'd ſo cloſe in the graſſe, of his game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome villany.</p>
               <p>This Beaſt (or rather Divell) for ſo hee ſeemes by his deſcription, by the ſtamping of his Oxe feete. Long teeth of Iron, nayles of Braſſe, and ten Hornes, or at leaſt ſome horrible Monſter in his likeneſſe, takes vpon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:16312:39"/>him to giue, by his Marke to all the world moſt curſed Diſpenſations: To pleaſe HE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROD it ſhall be lawfull to Marry his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to her Husbands owne Brother, the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to his Neece: Thus vnnaturall he is not ſatisfied in moſt prodigious manner to abuſe himſelfe, but others muſt doe Inceſtuouſly by his Example. Theſe vomited things, are now ſavory meate, neither can Sathan, caſt out Sathan: Then it is granted they can Erre, which Cunning leſſon had he not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of his lying Father, his Kingdome long ſince, had beene divided and broken in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Bee it never ſo vnlawfull, like the Law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> the Decree may not be changed.</p>
               <p>Thus out of the ſentences of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, this Spider ſucks ſomtimes his poyſon, ſaying in his Hart, All the Kingdoms of the <q>Earth are mine, My Father the Divell hath given them vnto me, and rather of my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate then abate a button; I will teach men as many lyes to damne them, as wee can both inuent, that with the breath of my Mouth I blow in and out the fire of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:16312:40"/>where People beleeue ſome Soules are blood-raw, others roſted to death, that I make the Creator, ſacrifice and ſell their Saviour, which puts me in minde of <hi>Iudas</hi> my Brother, whoſe hanging I could hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily lament, had hee not like a paſſionate foole, ſo ill playd his laſt part.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Admit of his weakneſſe he did repent, is a wiſe man the Trumpet of his owne ſhame? to ſay he had Err'd to be his owne accuſer, what did he gaine by this; ſome ſay forſooth, This Confeſſion of friends and foes, might be, to leaue the ſubtill El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and their generation the <hi>Iewes,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe, though wee eate both of one Sop, I like not the Example, I meane the manner; It is olde and weake, and lame Arguments will follow faſt enough; Idle Confeſſions, are no ſecrets to me, I like not his tragicall ſpeech, it was timorous, had it beene by boaſting, ſcoffing, or to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his ſervice, as it proued carneſt, more might bee ſaid in his defence. I doe the ſame my ſelfe: but let it paſſe, my plot was no pen to blot his name, and had it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:16312:40"/>the fire is witneſſe, his frailtie had never flowne ſo farre.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>When I call to minde my predeceſſors, no ſmall puffe can blow my pride downe, ſhall I degenerate, or not follow their ſteps, IUDAS the Apoſtle, and IULIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NUS the Emperour, no Ring-leaders of that Nazaren poore Sect, that leaue the certaine Bliſſe of this world, to beleeue 0253 200 Scripture promiſes made to the Fathers had I beene in their dayes, though they were couragious, both faithleſſe, and falſe enough, I can lift my heele as high as theirs, I had gone before them in their owne craft.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Yet ſince it was not remorce of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but the vngratefull anſwer of the chiefe Prieſts, and all his hopes fruſtrate, this caſt the Man away, my Pardon as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to him as to others, ſhall coſt him nothing, this accident vpon that ill advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed anſwer: WHAT IS THAT TO us LOOKE THOU TO THAT, was the firſt motiue that made me coine Abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which paſſeth now for currant Silver,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:16312:41"/>being all the Fees the deſperate Traitors get of mee towards their hanging, this ditch-water I giue the poore ſoules for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua-vitae, when they goe to the Gallowes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If ſome will ſay this ſtone is caſt too far, I ſay but a Dreame of like, or leſſe horror, would haue ſtarted, or as throughly awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned themſelues to behold ſo great a Tyrant, a Prince ſo gratious &amp; good, his Kingdome with ſo much pride, and ſpitefully invaded; All his naturall Subiects become diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Rebells, except a Remnant of ſome few, forſaking their liues, that lou'd not their liues to the Second Death, ſuffering for their loyalty &amp; loue vnexpreſſable, fiery exquiſite bloody torments, his Cittizens amongſt whom hee Inhabited, with one voyce Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out all at once. Away with this Man, ſaying, we will not haue this Man to raigne over vs, himſelfe (ô gentle Doue) dumbe as a Sheepe before the ſheerer, hanged by the hands as an off-ſcouring, ſet vp like a Marke for an Arrow, reviled, made a deriſion, as their Muſicke, to his People, ſweating drops of blood downe to the ground, the barres
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:16312:41"/>of ſorrow preventing the paſſage of Teares, (all in vaine) in ſo ſtrong and Agony, more for griefe and anguiſh of them and their Children? then his owne feare, of thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable paines and torments, Crying with a lowde voice, vnable to conceale that paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, MY GOD, MY GOD, VVHY HAST THOU FORSAKEN MEE, my tongue clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to my jawes, thou haſt brought me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the duſt of death through his tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſhedding from his pierced ſide, blood from the wound, for a ſenſible Teſtimony of a true Sacrifice, and water to Baptiſe and waſh them, whoſe hard hearts could not weepe for themſelues. He wiſte the Spirit of the Lord, was departed from him.</p>
               <p>Stones rent, the Earth quaking, not Ghoſts walking, but Graues opening, and dead Bodyes amazed, and awaking, The whole Globe Mourning in Sable blackneſſe, except Man, at the dreadfull Funerall of this moſt mighty Prince; The Sonne as Chiefe, covering and hiding his aſtoniſhed face, with hideous Cloudes, as blacke as Sackcloth of haire, to vtter the height and depth of ſilent
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:16312:42"/>ſpeaking ſorrow, by whoſe darke vaile and traine the ſhadow of Death, turning the Day to Night, wherein all Creatures are a Corps, and the world but a Tombe, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and abhorring his Beames of light ſhould beare witneſſe, the true light of Men, by mankinde was ſo vngratefully and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindely extinguiſhed, the expreſſe Pure I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the Maker, the Prince of life, The Perſon of God, (not made) turn'd to a lumpe of Clay, by a ſhameleſſe accuſation, an vnjuſt ſentence, and a curſed Executoner. To Slay theſe Lords that haue dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vs, hee pulled the houſe downe vpon his owne head, the mightie deliverer of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His God head and death being Incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, chooſing rather to forgoe, and forſake the one, then forget his promiſe, leaue the will of his Father vndone, or his worke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiſhed; His ſufferings being by a vacancy of Power, as ſometimes cold, may abate and aboliſh the ſenſe of feeling, yet retayned by the vitall parts, the loſſe is not irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>Whoſe Hart would not melt, Haire ſtare,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:16312:42"/>and Hands become faint, to write or heare ſuch a ſtory.</p>
               <p>Yet here is not an end, what ſhall he doe, now chaſed as a Bird betweene Heaven and Earth ſince his reſurrection, pull'd by Bitts to peeces, throwne to hungry Hell hounds, the Divells Dogs, Caniballs; did not his power to deliver his Darling, ſurmount the greedy arrogant policie of theſe <hi>Barbarians;</hi> ſpoken without aggravation both one Spaune, acting (in their Copes, I might ſay, party coloured fooles Coates) like painted Peacocks, the part of HECUBA, the fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Troyan Wiues and POLLIXINA; Such pompe and gaudineſſe of Masking gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, being fitter for the Theator then the Temple, the ſtate thereof requiring rather Mourners with all their BACCUS Savage Ceremonies, apiſh and affected Faſhions, No Vice on a Stage, with ſenſeleſſe jeſts to moue the vulgars laughter, good folkes aſhamed; So rediculous, without vnderſtanding bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling like Parrots or Children, a Tongue they know not; yet no Babes or Children in Mallice, Pyping without diſtinction; Prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:16312:43"/>not this the hearts of the hearers, twan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vpon a Harpe, Inſtead of an Egge, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Scorpion; and ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to any <hi>Pater-Noſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is there any ſorrow like this, whoſe Mirth is ſo great; whoſe heart ſo hard, as not to be greeved for this affliction; can wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to bow our ſelues, and not to Travell for theſe paines; To heare the Arke not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is taken, but helpe Lord alas, to ſee the Heire apparant of the living God ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and mangled amongſt his Enemies! O the wonder of wonders, a lying Wonder, to ſee creatures endued with ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, beleeue a ſenſleſſe Miracle; here is the Doctrine or ſpirits of Divells, three uncleane ſpirits, Three Frogs forg'd one like another, or a falſe lye ſpit vp by the Divell, the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet from their vncleane ſlimy Mouthes, Into the Ovens and knea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Troughs of the Kings of the Earth, and of the whole world, to gather them to the Battell of the great Day of God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; Alſo to decide the queſtion) with full conſent) when this doctrine working
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:16312:43"/>miracles was coniured vp. When Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors are come to the full; the water dried vp, that the way of the Kings of the Eaſt might bee prepared; The <hi>Tartars</hi> whoſe looke is more ſtout then his fellowes. Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous art thou ô Lord, which art, which waſt, and ſhall be, becauſe thou haſt iudged thus; for they haue ſhed the Blood of Saints and Prophets; and thou haſt given them vp to blaſpheme the God of Heaven, to beleeue a lye, falſe teachers that teach, thou haſt given them Blood to drinke; the Blood of the living God, as it were the Blood of a Dead man; here is a ſore lye, a grievous Soare, well may ſuch mad Dogs gnaw their Bliſtered Tongues.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall ſtand vp in his eſtate, a raiſer of Taxes in the glory of the Kingdome; but in few dayes hee ſhall bee deſtroyed in the ſtrength of his Age, neither in anger, nor in Battaile, but in a ſport of Tilting by a ſplinter in his Eye.</p>
               <p>And in his eſtate ſhall ſtand vp a vilde perſon, or a Luxurious, to whom they ſhall not giue the honour of the Kingdome, but
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:16312:44"/>he ſhall come in peaceably and obtayne the Kingdome by Flatterie; and with the Armes of a Flood, or as the ſodaine inundation of <hi>Nilus;</hi> ſo ſhall the Faithfull people be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowne from before him, they ſhall bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by a cruell Maſſacre, yea, alſo the Prince of the Covenant, and after the league made with him, even the Great King of the North, hee ſhall worke deceitfully with the holy people; for hee ſhall come vp and ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtrong with a ſmall people, he ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter peaceably even vpon the fatteſt places of the Province, for he ſhall doe that which his Fathers haue not done, nor his Fathers Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he ſhall ſcatter among them the prey, ſpoyle and riches of the wicked; yea, and he ſhall fore-caſt his devices againſt the ſtrong Holds of Sathan for a time, not to the End; And he ſhall ſtir vp his Power and his great Courage againſt the King of the South with a great Army, &amp; the King of the South ſhall be ſtirred vp to Battell with a very great and mightie Army, but hee ſhall not ſtand for they ſhall fore-caſt devices againſt him; yea, his owne Dogs (ſtiled Gods) that feed of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:16312:44"/>the Portion of his meate ſhall deſtroy him.</p>
               <p>After whoſe deceaſe his Army ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow, and many of the righteous ſhall fall downe ſlaine, and both theſe Kings hearts ſhalbe to doe miſchiefe, and they ſhall ſpeake lies againſt the knowne truth, both at one Table, but it ſhall not proſper; for yet the end of all things ſhall be at the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Then ſhall hee returne into his owne Land with great riches, and little profit; and his hart ſhall be againſt the holy Covenant; therefore the next blow was at the hart. And he ſhall doe exploits, and returne to his own Land.</p>
               <p>At the time appointed, hee ſhall returne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the King of the North ſpoken of before, that ſhould certainly come after certaine yeares with a great Army, and a multitude greater then the former with much riches, and ſhall come towards the South, but it ſhal not be as the former, or as the latter; for hee ſhall wound as it were his owne ſides. The Ships of Shittim ſhall come againſt him; therefore he ſhall be grieved and returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne ſtrength, and haue indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:16312:45"/>againſt the holy Covenants; So he ſhall doe; he ſhall returne, and haue intelligence with them that forſake the holy Covenant; theſe Ships built with pretious Wood, whoſe Anchor is the Lord, toſſed too and fro with flouds of vngodly men in the Sea of <hi>Babilon,</hi> and compaſſed with the Waues of death; but when they cry vnto the Lord, and are at their wits end. Hee who walketh vpon the Sea, draweth nigh vnto them, and bringeth them out of their diſtreſſe; hee maketh the ſtorme a calme, as a Childe, even ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſtilleth the roaring Waues of this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtious Sea, lifted vp with the ſtormy windes of Sathans malice.</p>
               <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord vnto <hi>Tyrus,</hi> O thou that art Scituate at the entry of the Sea; which art a Merchant for the People for many Iſles. Thus ſaith the Lord God; O <hi>Tyrus</hi> thou haſt ſaid, I am a perfect beautie. Thy Borders are in the midſt of the Seas, thy buildings haue perfected thy beautie; they haue made all thy Ship Boords all of Firre Trees of Senir; they haue taken Cedars from <hi>Libanan,</hi> to make Maſts for thee; of the Okes
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:16312:45"/>of <hi>Baſhan</hi> haue they made thine Oares; the Company of the <hi>Aſhurites</hi> haue made thy Benches of Ivorie, brought out of the Iſles of <hi>Chittim;</hi> Fyne Linnen with broydered worke from <hi>Egipt,</hi> was that which thou ſpreadeſt forth to bee thy Sayle, Blew and Purple from the Iſles of ELISHAH, was that which covered thee, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And Armies of the vngodly ſhall ſtand on his part; they ſhall pollute the Sanctuary of ſtrength, and ſhall take away the daily Sacrifice, and ſhall place therein the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that maketh the houſe of God deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, turning it into a Den of Theeues (the daily Sacrifice, or the Lords Supper ſhall be taken away to place the Divells Idoll, the Supper of the Lord, inſtituted in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our Redemption; as the Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was a Commemoration that the Lord paſſed over the houſes of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egipt,</hi> when hee ſmote the <hi>Egiptians</hi> and delivered them. DAVID a man after Gods own heart, poured out vnto the Lord, the Water of <hi>Bethelem,</hi> that he ſo ſore longed to drinke, the blood of Mortall men, that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:16312:46"/>went in jeopardy of their liues, yet damned people are told they drinke of God our Lord IESUS CHRIST his heart-blood. Shewing themſelues more thirſty after it, then the greedy <hi>Iewes,</hi> theſe blood-ſuckers will haue it before his ſide be pierced.</p>
               <p>And ſuch as doe wickedly againſt the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, to breake the Commandements of God, the vow, vowed in their Baptiſme, by which they forſake the Divell; with all the Covetous and Carnall deſires of the fleſh; theſe vncleane vilde perſons ſhall be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by flatteries, and eaſily drawne from the truth, to beleeue a lye, that they may bee damned, that hath pleaſure in vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but the People that know God and feare him, ſhall be ſtrong, he ſhall cover their heads in the day of Battaile, and they ſhall doe exploits, yet they that vnderſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the People, and their Teachers that inſtruct them; theſe ſhall fall by the ſword, and by flame and impriſonment, and by ſpoyle of their goods many dayes; yet feare none of theſe things, for hee that neither ſlumbers nor ſleepes, will ariſe and take his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:16312:46"/>owne quarrell into his hand, and you ſhall be holpen with a little helpe; Therfore truſt not in multitude of Forces, neither them that will cleaue to you with flatteries, for they will worke deceitfully, as they haue done in former times, nor expect a finall end of theſe perſecutions, Sathan will ſift, the tayle corne is his owne. If they call the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſe BELZEBUB, what reſpect can yee looke for that are of the houſhold. And in the King ſhall do according to his will, and hee ſhall exalt himſelfe and magnifie himſelfe aboue every God, and ſhall ſpeake marvellous things againſt the God of Gods, great words againſt the moſt High, and ſhall weare out the Saints of the Moſt high, and thinke to change times and Lawes, and ſhall proſper till the indignation bee accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, for that, that is determined ſhall bee done, Neither ſhall he regard the God of his Fathers, nor deſire of Women, neither ſhall ſhe retaine the power of the Arme, being a branch of vngrafted Roots; nor regard any God, but ſhall magnifie himſelfe aboue all; In his eſtate hee ſhall honour the God of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:16312:47"/>Forces and Battell, being terrible to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God and his Enemies; a God that his fore fathers knew not; or an Altar ſhall he honour with Gold and Silver, and with Pretious ſtones, and pleaſant things; thus ſhall hee doe in the moſt ſtrong holds with this God, a ſtranger for many yeares to the Apoſtles and their followers, whom he ſhall acknowledge and increaſe with glory; and hee ſhall cauſe in ſtead of Shepheards, Dogs and Wolues, in ſheep-skins, to rule over ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as Lords over Gods heritage, and they ſhall not onely devide the Land for filthy lucre, but make Merchandizes of mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. But if GOD ſpared not the Angels, what ſhall become of theſe curſed Children, that haue not onely loſt the Flocke, but gone aſtray and runne away themſelues, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the way of BALAM the Son of BOZER, who loved the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe, having eyes full of Adultery; even when they ſpeake their great ſwelling words of Vanitie and Abſolution; at that time they allure to the Luſts of the Fleſh, and much Wantonneſſe, leading ſimple women into
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:16312:47"/>Captivitie, promiſing libertie, that are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the ſervants of Corruption, wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Myre like filthy Swine to cleanſe themſelues by wreſting the Scriptures to their owne deſtruction, licking vp againe the vnſavorie meate themſelues could ill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt not long agoe, and running downe headlong into the deepe Lake of Fyre and Brimſtone, whoſe latter end is worſe then their beginning; it had beene better for theſe men to haue continued Heathens as they were at firſt in the pollutions of the world, then after they haue knowne the way of righteouſneſſe, to turne from it, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying the Sonne of God afreſh, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to open ſhame.</p>
               <p>And at the time of the End ſhall the King of the South puſh at him, with all his Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Pikes, and the King of the North ſhall come againſt him like a whirlewinde, with Chariots and with Horſemen, and with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ships, The Lord of Hoſts ſend them Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie; and he ſhall enter into the Countries, and ſhall overflow and paſſe over; hee ſhall enter alſo into the glorious Land <hi>Domina
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:16312:48"/>gentium,</hi> and many Countries ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne; but theſe ſhall eſcape out of his hand, even <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Moab,</hi> and the chiefe of the Children of AMMON his Confederates, he ſhall ſtretch forth his hand alſo vpon the Countries, and the Land of <hi>Egipt</hi> ſhall not eſcape; But hee ſhall haue powers over the Treaſures of Gold and of Silver, and over all the Precious things of <hi>Egipt,</hi> and the <hi>Libians</hi> and the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> ſhall bee at his ſteps. But tidings out of the Eaſt and out of the North ſhall trouble him, therfore he ſhall goe forth with a great furie to deſtroy and vtterly to make away many; And hee ſhall plant the Tabernacles of his Cedars Pallace betweene the Seas in the glorious holy Mountaine; yet he ſhall come to his end, and none ſhall helpe him.</p>
               <p>Therefore take vp a lamentation for the King of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> whoſe Cedars are for the building of both Houſes; and ſay thou haſt beene in EDEN the Garden of GOD; every pretious Stone to garniſh the foundation was thy Covering, the Ruby, the Topaz, and the Diamond, the Berill, the Onix, the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:16312:48"/>Iaſper and the Saphire, theſe things were prepared for thee. Thou art annointed the Cherube that Covereth, thou waſt vpon the holy Mountaine of GOD, and thou haſt walked vp and downe in the middeſt of the Stones of Fyre: but becauſe thou haſt lifted vp thy heart, and ſaid; I am GOD, I haue ſubdued three Kings. I ſit in the middeſt of the Seas, and haſt defiled thy ſacred Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, I will bring thee to Aſhes, and none ſhall help thee. As I liue, ſaith the Lord, I will even doe according to thine anger, and according to thine Envie, which thou haſt vſed out of thy hatred againſt them, and I will make my ſelfe knowne amongſt them, when I haue judged thee, and thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord, and that I haue heard all thy Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, which thou haſt ſpoken againſt the Mountaine of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> Saying, they are layd deſolate by Maſſacre, they are given vs to conſume by the ſword; thus with thy mouth thou haſt Boaſted againſt Mee, therefore ſhortly when the whole Land of <hi>Iſraell</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth, I will make thee deſolate, then thou ſhalt know that I the LORD doe Sanctifie
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:16312:49"/>
                  <hi>Iſraell,</hi> when my Sanctuary ſhall bee in the middeſt of them for ever.</p>
               <p>Therefore, ô King of the North, ariſe from thy Throne, lay thy Royall Robe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and cauſe a Decree through <hi>Tyrus</hi> to be publiſhed; ſaying, Let them turne every one from his evill way, and from the violence or vnnaturall ſhedding of Blood, that is in their hands, &amp;c. Who can tell if GOD will turne and repent, and turne away from his fierce anger, that wee goe not into Perdition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>DANIEL.</hi> CHAP. XII. IAMES, CHARLES — ARE MICHAELSS.</head>
               <p>AND at that time ſhall MICHAEL ſtand vp, the great Prince that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends the Faith, CHARLES King of Great <hi>Britaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> which ſtandeth for the faithfull Children of our Nation, the Saints of the moſt Higheſt. As the Angell of God, ſo is my Lord the King, to diſcerne good and bad; therefore the Lord thy God will be with thee for ever.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:16312:49"/>
               <p>And there ſhall be a time of trouble, ſuch as never was ſince there was a Nation, even to that ſame time, bleſſings and great felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, being for the moſt part accompanied with Corrections, and extraordinary Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; Devotion and Religion of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in this life the Higheſt, not exempt from ſuperſtition and hereſie; And at that time thy People ſhall bee delivered; Every one whoſe name is found written in the Booke, &amp;c.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a crown</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>AL TRVTHS CESAR.</p>
               <p>Behold the Lord is at the Dore, as a man come from a farre journey; All that ſleepe in the Duſt of the Earth, ſhall heare his voyce and awake, and come forth, thoſe that haue done good to the Reſurrection of life; Theſe haue their part in the firſt Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thoſe that haue done evill vnto the Reſurrection of Damnation. Then the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell came downe from Heaven, hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the falſe Prophet the Key of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:16312:50"/>Bottomleſſe pit, having in his hand a great Chaine, hee ſhall next lay hold on the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon the Devill; and hee ſhall bee bound a Thouſand yeares, or one day, which is all one with the Lord; he ſhall ſhut him vp, and ſet a Seale vpon him, for the wrath of the Lord that day, ſhall bee a ſufficient marke that the Nations be deceived no more.</p>
               <p>This Thouſand yeares is the great day of the Lord, to poure out his wrath and juſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation vpon his Enemies; But the wiſe Virgins with Palmes in their hands, that haue not beene deceived by the ſubtilty or force of flatterers, ſhall ſhine in their Robes, as the brightneſſe of the Firmament; Kings Daughters attended by honourable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, as Starres for ever and ever, prepared for the Bridegroomes Marriage, whoſe Wife the Bride and Queene, hath made her ſelfe ready clothed in fine Linnen cleane and white, arrayed in a Garment of Needle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke wrought with Gold of Ophier, the Daughter of <hi>Tyre</hi> ſhall bee there with a Gift; ſhe ſhall be brought to the King, with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and reioycing, they ſhall enter into his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:16312:50"/>Pallace, ſaying, O King, thy Throne is for ever and ever, thou loveſt righteouſneſſe and hateſt wickedneſſe; therefore God thy God annoynt thee with gladneſſe aboue thy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <p>After this Thouſand yeares the great Day of the ſolemnitie finiſhed, the Bride being ſafe in her cloſſet and Marriage chamber, Sathan the olde Serpent ſhall be looſed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſeaſon, as Priſoners are ſet at libertie when they goe to the place of Execution to receiue his finall ſentence of everlaſting Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet hoping in his vaine imagination and hart that cannot repent to deceiue the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are at reſt, to take a prey, to goe vp to the Citie that is in ſafetie that needs no Wall, neither the light of the Sunne or the Moone, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Vnto whom the juſt Iudge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Throne of Glory with a terrible looke, for furie, jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie ſhall come vp into his face, ſhall ſay vnto him; Art thou he whom I haue ſpoken of in olde time by my ſervants the Prophets to giue the Nations warning of thee, how thou diddeſt not onely like a foole deceiue
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:16312:51"/>thy ſelfe, when thou ſaidſt, I will aſcend vp and be like the moſt higheſt, but like a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed creature didſt deceiue their innocent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, be prepared therefore, and prepare thy ſelfe and all thy Company, and ſee whether thou canſt be a guard vnto them; or what defence they can make for themſelues who could not be ignorant, and ought not to be careleſſe, becauſe by mine owne Mouth I gaue them warning, that after many dayes thou ſhouldſt be viſited and brought a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner into the Land which is now brought backe from the Sword and cleanſed, though it lay waſte a time, and the Villages thereof vnwalled. For theſe I commanded them ſtraightly to watch both concerning the things I fore-told them ſhould come to paſſe; as alſo of this houre, leſt like a Theefe, or as the Flood came vpon their fore-fathers the Vngodly, they ſhould be ſurpriſed vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, becauſe I told you of theſe things before depart, I know yee not, nor that Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine your falſe Prophet, are yee thoſe that eate my fleſh and drinke my blood, whence are yee, I never knew you more, then you
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:16312:51"/>knew mine, or Me; curſed and deformed crew, with ſtiffe neckes, double crooked hearts, deafe Adders, and blinde People with eyes, goe yee curſed into everlaſting fire.</p>
               <p>Wee haue eaten and Drunke in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, all the world was taxed by the Prince of our Nation; and thou haſt taught in our ſtreets; Their iniquitie is the greater, thruſt them out. Lord, Lord, come out Dogs and Swine, Apes and Satiers, hence here all Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Scoffers at the truth, vncleane perſons, for here ſhall enter in no wiſe any thing that defileth, neither whatſoever worketh Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, or maketh a Lye, but they which are written in the Lambes Booke of Life.</p>
               <p>But thou ô DANIEL, ſhut vp the words, and ſeale vp this Booke to the time of the end; Now that the whole world might take notice, and diſcerne when this Sealed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie ſhall be opened, the time is more then once repeated, even at the time is more then once repeated, even at the time of the end, when the King of the South ſhall puſh at the King of the North, and the King of the North ſhall come againſt him like a Whirle-winde, for till then, though many ſhall run
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:16312:52"/>too and fro by the Art of Navigation, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering an other Hemiſphere, Sayling by the Compaſſe and the Needle, found out by expert men, and knowledge increaſed, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Magnificent Libraries with printed Bookes, By which two Arts, chiefly the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſhall bee publiſhed to all Nations; yet the Character of this Booke ſhall not bee read, till the time of the end; which time is eaſie to be knowne, even without the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the yeares cloſed vp in this Booke; where Eagles are gathered together, you ſuppoſe ſome Carcaſſe to be there: The Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, when her Branch is yet tender, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth her leaues, ye know that Summer is neere; <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> when it was compaſſed with Armies, the Deſolation was nigh. In like manner, when yee ſee theſe things come to paſſe fore-told you, know the end is nie, even at the dore; But of the day and houre knoweth no man, no not the Angells that are in Heaven; neither the Sonne but the Father; the accompt in this Booke of note, being by Centuries of yeares.</p>
               <p>Then I DANIEL looked, and behold
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:16312:52"/>there ſtood other Two; the two Oliue Trees, the Tree of Life, either of them bearing Twelue manner of Fruites, the Two Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes into whom, after Three dayes and a halfe, the Spirit of Life from God entred; and they ſtood vpon their feet. The one on this ſide of the banke of the River; and the other on that ſide of the bank of the River; The fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dations of the wall of the City, Ieſus Chriſt himſelf being the chiefe corner ſtone.</p>
               <p>And one ſaid to the man clothed in Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, that was vpon the waters of the Rivers, that cryed with a loude voyce, as when a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Roareth; Lord wilt thou at this time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore againe the Kingdome of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> how long ſhall it be to the end of theſe wonders, or tell vs when theſe things ſhall bee, and what ſhall bee the ſigne of thy comming, and of the end of the world.</p>
               <p>And he held vp his right hand and his left hand to Heaven, ſhewing his Reſurrection and Aſcention, and ſware by him that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for ever and ever, Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but my Word ſhall not paſſe, neither this froward generation; this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:16312:53"/>Nation till all theſe things bee done ſpoken of by my Mouth and the Prophets; there be ſome ſtanding here, which ſhall not taſte of Death, till they ſee the Sonne of Man comming in his Kingdome, his ſervants will fight for him. So ſhall even all my words be fulfilled.</p>
               <p>It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons which the Father hath put in his owne power; But goe thou thy way and reſt, and ſtand in the Lot. Seale vp thoſe things which the Seven thunders vttered, and write them not, it ſhall be for a time and times and halfe, then all theſe things ſhall be finiſhed, as a Henne gathereth her Chickens, or as a ſcattered Army in that day the Holy People ſhall be gathered together, in the meane time many ſhall bee purified and made white by the fiery Tryall; The wicked ſhall doe wickedly, and ſhall not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, but the wiſe, it is given vnto them to vnderſtand the miſteries of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven.</p>
               <p>And from the time that the daily Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſhall bee taken away, or the yearely
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:16312:53"/>Paſſeover by the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to place the Abomination that maketh deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late; there ſhall be a Thouſand Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and Ninetie dayes; Heere is the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Temple, and the Altar, and them that worſhip therein; And here is alſo the breach of the firſt Commandements, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by our Lord; the abomination that maketh deſolate not only the Sanctuary but the Citie; the firſt ripe Apples that hang ſo high againſt the Sunne; The Divell thought if hee could reach theſe, the reſt were his owne; therefore to plucke them downe in the primitiue times, he began to reare his Ladder in the holy Places to ſet vp his plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, adding the Images of living Mortall men to be worſhipped with Divine honour, and vaine ſupplications, as if themſelues were preſent, making no doubt, hauing no egreſſe and regreſſe in time to bring his owne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them into the nomber, in which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation hee fayled not much; for who is this here, that ſits in the Temple of God, as if there were Two Gods, beſides his PIG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MALION-like Image; the parts of which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:16312:54"/>are ſeldome colde, if there bee heate in the Kiſſes of ſuch holy People.</p>
               <p>The ſwiftneſſe of time is ſuch, I cannot gather all the Spices and dropping Myrrhe of this Tree, I can fixe no longer ſpeaking what manner God will ſit alone in his holy Temple, abhorring not only the people but the place where a Coleague is joyned with him in office; therefore of the next branch.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe a man after his Marriage to a young Virgin, ſhould ſay, my experience is more then yours. I cannot alwayes walke hand in hand with you, neither may I keepe you in a Cloiſter that will not be for your health or my profit, neither muſt you forget your Covenant to bee ſubiect to my deſires not tending to the harme of either of vs; I loue you as mine owne Body, if I ſhould not loue you, I ſhould not loue my ſelfe; you are tender and faire without ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh or blot, ſo I would haue your minde alſo without ſpot or wrinckle like your face, many ſtrangers will ſtriue to bee your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; not all for your beautie but ſome for malice and enuie to me: Though your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:16312:54"/>be good in all things, yet becauſe I am very jealous of mine honor, entertaine none in that manner; though they be ſilent for a time, and conceale themſelues, in the end they will draw your affection from me; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, much reſort though ſhee be never ſo chaſte, is dalliance the marke of a knowne Harlot, which ſort of women I would haue you differ from, and no marke I know more fit to put a difference betweene you then this; For much entertainment will not only waſte our ſubſtance, better imployed vpon more neceſſary occaſions, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume time in vnprofitable idleneſſe.</p>
               <p>Is there no conſequent, yes doubtleſſe, I am the Lord thy God, thou ſhalt haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods but me; thou ſhalt not make I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of any likeneſſe to bowe or humble thy ſelfe before them; for of my honor I am a jealous God, you are mine, I bought you to enioy the libertie of my ſervice; I brought yee out of the houſe of bondage, which no other God could doe; thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God, and keepe his charge and his Statutes.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:16312:55"/>
               <p>When yee goe forth to ſhew the way of truth to other Nations, this ſpirituall dalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which in the end turnes to whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, beware of it for it ſhall bee a marke betweene them that hate mee and you that keepe my Comandements; and though I will not at any time bee farre from you, yet you ſhall fall by Captivitie and perſecution to ſpread my name, or for the Triall of your Faith, when you ſee their Idolatrie pull downe their high Places, Preach againſt them; ſay, Little Children, ignorant people that vnderſtand not the ſlights of Sathan; Beware of Idols, tender natures encounter ſtrongeſt motions; Top-ſayles are firſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted; No man ſo well knowes his owne frailtie, as the Lord your God knowes how prone Devotion is to Superſtition.</p>
               <p>Alſo when yee goe in and out amongſt the Heathen folke, or if the Lord giue them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your hands, as the <hi>Amalikites</hi> were given into the hand of the Children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> when the Prophet ſaid; what meaneth this blea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in mine eares; SAULS excuſe ſhall not availe you; to ſay, we ſet them vp for Saints
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:16312:55"/>before the Lord, the Images of IUPITER for Ieſus Chriſt; the Statue of HERCULES for CHRISTOPHER; VENUS and the little Lad, for the bleſſed Virgin, as holy as Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crowes in a Garden of Cowcumbers.</p>
               <p>You that cannot make one haire white or blacke, will yee goe a Whoring after your owne inventions, to humble your ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Pageants, Pictures, Images with eyes that ſee not, Eares without hearing, &amp;c. More ſenſleſſe then a Beaſt; yet theſe rare Mamets, the light of the Sunne is too darke for them without Candles; when the Members of Chriſt goe naked, theſe muſt bee cloathed, not for warmneſſe but for wantonneſſe; and theſe are the Babyes made and dreſſed by the Divell, and decked to pleaſe his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, abhorred, and abominable in the ſight of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, with theſe lines the Temple of God is Meaſured, and them that worſhip therein. Meaſuring is for Numbering; place is put for time, and ſometimes ſpace a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſixe hundred furlongs; Signifying the perſecution of the Church ſo many yeares,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:16312:56"/>reward her even as ſhe rewarded you. To riſe therefore and Meaſure the time, begin from the taking away of the daily Sacrifice or the Deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and count a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred and threeſcore yeares, wherein for the abſence of the Church in the Wilderneſſe, the two Witneſſes did Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie clothed in Sackcloth, ſo many yeares of Miſts and darkneſſe, to theſe muſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſome dayes of faire weather, a hundred forty and foure thouſand, amounting to foure hundred yeares and odde, having their fathers name written in their foreheads, theſe ſing as it were a new ſong; Theſe are Virgins not (defiled with women) Chaſte converſation, not commanding laciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by forbidding Marriage, waxing worſe and worſe.</p>
               <p>The Temple was not built in a day, it is three Stories; the foure hundred yeares are to be devided into three ſeverall parts, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty yeares and odde, vntill the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when the Apoſtles finiſhed their teſtimony, thirty yeares are reſtored for the raigne of CONSTANTINE the great, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:16312:56"/>remaine for theſe laſt times, being the ſame eighteene thouſand Meaſures ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by EZEKIEL the Prophet, the Meaſure of the Temple within are not ſummed vp, I preſume not to looke into the account, the Meaſure of it round about without, I heard the number of them caſt vp, Eighteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Meaſures, every Meaſure ſixe Cubits, according to the Meaſure of a man. That is, of the Angell, three hundred yeares &amp; odde; and the name of the City from that day ſhal bee God is there, that ſaid Son of Man, the place of my Throne, and the place of the ſoles of my feet, where I will dwell in the middeſt of the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> for ever, and my holy Name ſhall the houſe of <hi>Iſraell</hi> no more defile, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed is he that waiteth and commeth to the thouſand three hundred and fiue and thirty yeares, theſe are the bleſſed times of IOHN WICKLIFFE &amp; IOHH Hus, both fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Martyrs, and burning Lights, ſet vp to ſhew forth the ſtate and beauty of the truth, one burnt aliue, the other after hee was dead, being hard to judge in which of theſe,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:16312:57"/>the Devill the Father of lyes, Antichriſt his crucifying Sonne, and the Dragon, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed moſt malice; from which curſed tripli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, three Monſters of the bottomleſſe Pit, God deliver vs, who will giue vs a Crowne of life; Come Lord IESUS, the grace of our Lord IESUS CHRIST bee with you all.</p>
               <p>Amen.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, the whole world is numbred and thoſe that worke abomination therein, and the delights thereof, weighed in the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances, are found lighter then vanitie it ſelfe. There is nineteene yeares and a halfe to the day of Iudgement, Iuly the 28. M.DC.XXV. Sixe hundred and threeſcore Moneths are excluded, from this laſt Age of ſeventeene hundred yeares. And I thinke that I haue alſo the Spirit of God.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>DANIEL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>Hee that is vniuſt and filthy let him bee ſo ſtill, and hee that is righteous and holy, let him bee ſo ſtill; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold hee will come quickly, and his reward is with him. Bleſſed are they that doe his Commandements.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16312:57"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
